<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Piety the best rule of orthodoxy, or, An essay upon this proposition, that the conduciveness of doctrines to holiness or vice is the best rule for private Christians to judge the truth or falshood of them by in a letter to his honoured friend H.M. / by Hen. Hesketh.</title>
            <author>Hesketh, Henry, 1637?-1710.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43454</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1613</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27424</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09851526</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09851526</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44247</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43454)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44247)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1359:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Piety the best rule of orthodoxy, or, An essay upon this proposition, that the conduciveness of doctrines to holiness or vice is the best rule for private Christians to judge the truth or falshood of them by in a letter to his honoured friend H.M. / by Hen. Hesketh.</title>
                  <author>Hesketh, Henry, 1637?-1710.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 129 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Piety.</term>
               <term>Spiritual life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44247:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44247:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PIETY THE Beſt Rule OF ORTHODOXY.</p>
            <p>OR, An Eſſay upon this Propoſition: That the Conduciveneſs of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines to Holineſs or Vice, is the beſt Rule for private Chriſtians to judge the Truth or Falſhood of them by.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a Letter to his Honoured Friend</hi> H. M.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Clem. Alexand.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Hen. Hesketh, <hi>Vicar of S.</hi> Hellens, <hi>and Chaplain to his Majeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the Biſhops-Head in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:44247:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44247:2"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THE Introduction.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The great need of every Chriſtians taking heed of Error. The difficulty in our preſent circumſtances of doing ſo. The greatneſs of that charity that endeavours to aſſiſt men in order thereto. The pitching upon a rule whereby every man may do this, from that place of S. <hi>John, 1 John 4.6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The Collection drawn from the preceeding Text: That Piety is the beſt rule of Orthodoxy. The ſence in which the propoſition is to be underſtood. Two Poſtulata's in order to the proof of it. God hath provided ſuch a rule for men
<pb facs="tcp:44247:3"/>
to judge by, and the reaſons urging a belief that he hath done ſo. This rule muſt be for the benefit and guidance of all men.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Two ways propoſed for the proof of the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, Scripture and Reaſon. This Text improved largely to this purpoſe, and <hi>Mat. 7.16.</hi> of which a full explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is endeavoured.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> The old Teſtament cited alſo for the proof of this, and two great conſiderations added to give more Evidence to it. This the rule to try Prophets by of old, and the beſt Criterion of a true Divine Miracle.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> A further diſcourſe of Miracles, and their Evidence, and how to know which are Divine, and which are not. An addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all from the Nature of Hereſie,
<pb facs="tcp:44247:3"/>
and wherein the Notion of it doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The Arguments from reaſon for the proof of the Collection: Four propoſed; and Two inſiſted on in this Chapter: The firſt taken from the end of theſe Two Spirits in the World: The ſecond from the great deſign of Chriſtian Religion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The third and fourth Arguments propoſed: The Inconvenience of ſubſtituting any other rule but this, and the manifeſt advantage of this above any that can be ſubſtituted.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Six rules laid down to be obſerved by us in our judging by this rule, and three of them inſiſted on. <hi>1.</hi> That we conſider the Doctrines only, and not the men that maintain them. <hi>2.</hi> That we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Doctrines not only in themſelves, and appearances, but alſo in their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb facs="tcp:44247:4"/>
and direct conſequences. <hi>3.</hi> That we be ſincere and unprejudiced in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, and do not allow our ſelves to pervert and wreſt them.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> The other three rules inſiſted on. <hi>1.</hi> That doctrines and modes of Religion formed by them be not conſidered only in ſome ſingle inſtances, but complexly and fully in all, eſpecially thoſe in which they differ from others. <hi>2.</hi> That men have a right notion of holineſs. <hi>3.</hi> That holineſs be conſidered not only in its immediate ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, but alſo with all the helps, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages and encouragements to it.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Some Inferences made from this Collection, particularly a Vindication of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which may juſtly challenge any Sect at this day to joyn iſſue with it upon this Principle.</item>
               <item>The Concluſion.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:44247:4"/>
            <head>THE INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AMongſt thoſe very many Sweet and Guſtful Reliſhes that the Senſe of your Friendſhip leaves upon my Spirits, The freſh diſcoveries that I every day make of your real worth and Goodneſs, is truly the greateſt.</p>
            <p>And certainly that man oweth much to Providence, and his recognitions to it, can hardly equal the Bleſſing, that hath the good hap to contract Intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Friendſhips, of which he finds no reaſons afterwards to repent and be aſhamed, and to which he needs not ſtudy to put any Interruptions. And this is the caſe of every man who hath a worthy man, and a good man to his Friend, and it is at preſent mine.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:44247:5"/>Sir, I do not intend to flatter you in this, I know that would be the ſureſt way to make my ſelf more unworthy of ſuch a felicity than I am. Nor do I intend to take the meaſures of your worth from any things, but ſuch as are certain, and will aſſure ſuch deducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. I do not proclaim you worthy and Good becauſe you are rich, and kind, and affable, and courteous, and ſtudious as becomes a Philoſopher:</p>
            <p>But I do this becauſe you are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for Religion, and are tender of mens Eternal Intereſts, and have a dear reſpect to Souls, and would have all men partake of thoſe felicities, of which your great Piety procures you many bleſſed Antepaſts now, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance in that piety will aſſure your full and perfect fruition afterwards.</p>
            <p>And truly Sir, theſe are things which in every age have reflected ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour upon men, but will much more do ſo in this. For a Gentleman to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any ſenſe of Religion now, when unconcernedneſs for it is ſo much the mode, and ſcoffing at every thing that
<pb facs="tcp:44247:5"/>
is Sacred, ſo much the common enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, and ſo hugely gratifying to the <hi>Genius</hi> of the Age. To be ſolicitous for humane Souls, when ſo many are ready to queſtion whether they have any or no; and of thoſe that profeſs to believe they have, yet ſo very few are pleaſed to have any regards for their welfare. To be ſtudying and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving helps and advantages for them in their progreſs to Heaven, when the disbelief of any future ſtate hath ſo much obtained, and when it is counted wit, and a <hi>ſpecimen</hi> of parts, to buffoon and droll all thoughts of it out of the breaſts of men.</p>
            <p>To do all theſe things with ſincerity and zeal, which perhaps will meet with no better entertainment than de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion or ſcorn, is certainly an evidence of a great and fixed goodneſs, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders you little leſs worthy of that praiſe, which the Spirit of God was pleaſed to give <hi>Job</hi> for being perfect at <hi>Luz,</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> for retaining his purity in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:44247:6"/>I ſhall not ſo far treſpaſs upon your Humility and Modeſty as to mention all the Inſtances, in which theſe things diſcover themſelves. This that your preſent commands (for ſo I always in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret a Friends deſires) require of me, is alone enough. It is to give you my thoughts, what I judge to be the beſt Criterion of truth, and by what marks a man might moſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcover it, in this miſt, and great duſt, that the eager Contentions, and tumultuous diſputings of men have raiſed about it, and obſcured it in: And by what methods a private Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſhould proceed in this amazing diverſity of Opinions, and from whence take his meaſures of truth and ſafety.</p>
            <p>This is (if I miſtake not much) an act of ſuch kindneſs, that it is not eaſie for you to ſhew, or men to receive a greater; and if I can do any ſervice to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards reallizing the effects of it, I do not well know many inſtances, in which I may more ſafely rejoyce.</p>
            <p>And truly as for that reaſon I do the more willingly, ſo for another I can
<pb facs="tcp:44247:6"/>
the more eaſily comply with your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and miniſter ſomething to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this great purpoſe, becauſe it ſo falls out, that I ſhall but recollect my thoughts, and tranſcribe (with very little variation) what I have delivered not long ago in my own Congregation on this ſubject. And therefore I muſt beg you to accept ſome Sermon-Notes inſtead of a formal Letter, and to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me, that I addreſs to you as one of my own People. Only Sir, my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects will not ſuffer me to thruſt you into the common croud; ſomething will be added which was not then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, and you will perceive it, by being addreſſed only to your ſelf.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:44247:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44247:7"/>
            <head>PIETY The Beſt Rule of ORTHODOXY.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The great need of every Chriſtians taking heed of Error. The difficulty in our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent circumſtances of doing ſo. The greatneſs of that Charity that endeavours to aſſiſt in order thereunto. The pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon a Rule whereby every man may do, from that place of the Apoſtle S. <hi>John, 1 John 4.6.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE that ſeriouſly conſiders what the condition of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is at this day in that part of the World that calls it ſelf
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:44247:8"/>
Chriſtian; how almoſt all the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations therein are divided among themſelves, and have conſiderable dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences upon the account of which they ſeparate each from other, forming themſelves into diſtinct Societies, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their different Sentiments, and ways of Worſhip.</p>
               <p>And withal conſiders how confident all parties are of the truth and ſafety of their own way, with how much cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and noiſe they plead for it, and with how much confidence they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim againſt all that is oppoſite to it. While he is certain that ſome (yea a great many) of them are certainly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken; it being impoſſible that ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and ſo very contrary ways ſhould all be true.</p>
               <p>He, I ſay, that ſeriouſly conſiders all this, may very well ſubſcribe to the reaſonableneſs of that excellent advice of our Bleſſed Lord, when predicting theſe things, <hi>Take heed and beware that no man deceive you:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.4.</note> And may very well look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Ingemination, not only as deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:44247:8"/>
to enhance his care that he be not deceived; but as an intimation alſo how difficult it will be to avoid his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo.</p>
               <p>And truly he that hath any due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to his own Soul, or any juſt ſenſe of the preſent ſtate of things, muſt needs ſubſcribe to the juſtneſs of the Ingemination upon both accounts.</p>
               <p>For the welfare of the Soul in all its actings, doth mightily depend upon the Principles that it chuſeth to act by, and theſe are only then ſafe, when they are the reſults of a ſound and right judgment, which that judgment can never be, that is Impoſed upon by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, and cheated by Error. So that the neceſſity of attending unto the Caution upon that ſole account is very great.</p>
               <p>And yet that neceſſity is heightened much by the other, for where there are various ways that offer themſelves to us, and none of theſe want their ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pretences, but are recommended to us with all poſſible art and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, there the chuſing and hitting
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44247:9"/>
upon the right, muſt needs be difficult, and the avoiding deception not very eaſie.</p>
               <p>The Conſideration of theſe two things, hath cauſed me oftentimes, with ſome more than ordinary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, to reflect upon the Condition of a private ordinary Chriſtian at this time, and with a great deal of pity, to compare his ſtate, to that of a Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler in an unknown road, full of many various and different turnings, which muſt not only needs diſtract and puzle his thoughts which of them to chuſe, but create in him a great deal of fear leſt he chuſe amiſs.</p>
               <p>And as compaſſion naturally enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to charity, and pitying a mans miſery prompts us to thoughts how to redreſs it: So I have many times thought with my ſelf, that man would do a good office, and a thing hugely conducive to the welfare of men, that could pitch upon and preſcribe a way, how to remedy this great Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with eaſe and ſafety.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:44247:9"/>For as the erecting the <hi>Statuae Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riales</hi> (by the Ancient <hi>Romans</hi>) in all common Roads, upon which were not only ſteps by which Travellers might mount their Beaſts and go on, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions alſo to direct them which were the right paths, was then accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and is to this day remembred as a very high inſtance of the kindneſs and candor of that great people. So cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the doing the like in this caſe for the poor Chriſtian Traveller, would be ſo much the greater inſtance of charity, by how much his way is more perplex'd and intricate, and the danger of his erring the greater and more momentous.</p>
               <p>He that ſhall undertake to do this for him, may well expect his prayers for his ſucceſs, and if he ſhould erre in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his utmoſt in it, may as well hope for his compaſſion and pardon: If it can be done, it is really a great benefit, and the deſign of it a great charity; and if a man chance to erre in it, yet an error that reſults from charity, may well expect a gentle and candid cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:44247:10"/>How to do this hath been a thing that hath long lain upon my thoughts, and a caſe that I have much conſulted about, I have been thinking what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to pitch upon, what to ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute that might bear the ſtreſs of ſuch an Enquiry, what Oracle to erect, to which men might ſafely commit the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of all difficulties of this nature, and with confidence repair unto, for a full and ſafe ſatisfaction in them.</p>
               <p>What the iſſue of all theſe conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and thoughts hath been I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined (this <hi>Lent</hi>) to acquaint you withal. And I ſhall take the riſe of what I purpoſe to deliver to you of this nature, from the words of the great S. <hi>John,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 4.6.</note> who lived to ſee the actual accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Lord's great prediction, that falſe Prophets ſhould come into the world, and had the honour to be the great preſcriber of Antidotes againſt the infection of thoſe deceivers. And in that very place where he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely undertakes this, doth preſcribe what I am now going to inſiſt upon as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44247:10"/>
a ſure remedy, a certain Criterion by which we may judge: <hi>Hereby know we the Spirit of truth, and the Spirit of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The Collection drawn from the preceeding Text. Piety the beſt Rule of Orthodoxy. The ſenſe in which the Propoſition is to be underſtood. Two Poſtulata's in order to the proof of it. God hath provided ſuch a Rule for men to judge by, and the reaſons urging a belief that he hath done ſo. This Rule muſt be for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and guidance of all men.</head>
               <p>FOR theſe words of S. <hi>John,</hi> I think we may ſafely draw this Collection, <hi>Piety is the beſt Rule of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxy,</hi> or plainer thus, <hi>The Condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civeneſs of Doctrines unto Godlineſs is the beſt and ſafeſt Rule by which to judge the truth of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:44247:11"/>But before I enter immediately upon the larger handling of this Propoſition, I ſhall ſtay you a little while, that I may give you the full of what I mean, when I thus ſpeak. For as the Text ſpeaks both of the Spirit of truth and of error, ſo I ſhall underſtand the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition both ways, with reference to both theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Directly and poſitively. The Spirit of truth enclines to holineſs, and every doctrine that proceeds from this Spirit, doth ſome way or other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to that great end. And when doctrines, upon trial, are found to be ſubſervient to make men good and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly holy, then they bear the ſtamp and impreſs of truth upon them, and this is a ſafe way by which to judge the truth of them, and conclude them Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Oppoſitely or negatively. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Doctrine or Opinion doth tend to the contrary, either teaching or encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging ſin and diſobedience in all or in any one particular inſtance of it, is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly falſe, and proceeds from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44247:11"/>
of Error, and let men be never ſo zealous for it, and confident in recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending and obtruding of it upon others, yet this is a ſufficient warrant for every private Chriſtian to reject it, and condemn it as ſpurious and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous: For the Spirit of Error inclines men to diſobedience, and whatever do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine doth ſo, doth proceed from it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Comparatively. Thus where dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Doctrines and Opinions offer themſelves to us, it is a ſafe way to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine carefully which of them condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth moſtly to make men good, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly to make our eſtimate of them; accepting that which is beſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with holineſs, and a neceſſity of it, and rejecting that which is any way failing herein.</p>
               <p>And now by this you may ſee my ſenſe of the Propoſition, how I make obedience and holineſs the Shekel of the Sanctuary, by which all other meaſures are to be tried. I make Gods Law not only the Rule of what ought to be done, but I would have every thing that is to be believed brought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44247:12"/>
it, examin'd how it comports with it, and is ſubſervient to the great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of it, and according either to be accepted or rejected.</p>
               <p>But before I come to ſhew the truth and reaſonableneſs of this Aſſertion, and to prove this to be the ſafeſt Rule for all Chriſtians to judge and examine Truth and Error by; there are Two things which I ſhall lay down as <hi>Poſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lata</hi>'s, or things intimated to us from this Text, and of great advantage in order to the aſſuring the truth of the great Propoſition.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That God hath left us ſome Rule to judge the truth and falſhood of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and Doctrines by.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That this Rule is obvious and plain, and intended for the guidance and benefit of all men.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That God hath not left us with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome ſure Rule to judge the truth and falſhood of Opinions and Doctrines by: This is a truth, which no man that hath any honourable and becoming Sentiments of the goodneſs and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, can in any meaſure doubt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44247:12"/>
of. He whoſe gracious Providence watcheth over all things, certainly is regardful alſo of man. He that hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted and put ſuch an inſtinct into the nature of all other things, as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables them to know what is beneficial and hurtful to their reſpective natures, and according to purſue and embrace the one, and avoid and arm themſelves againſt the other; hath certainly not been wanting to man in this great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but enabled him to diſcern truth from falſhood, as well as good from evil, and to do both theſe in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality as well as Nature, <hi>i. e.</hi> to judge for his Soul as well as his Body.</p>
               <p>And the truth is, if it were other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, man were of all things certainly the moſt miſerable, and a Religious man were the moſt miſerable and piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able above all other men. And it would reflect great diſhonour upon God, to provide for the ſafety and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of man in all his little concerns; but to leave him wholly unprovided for, and expoſed to deception in that which is the moſt ſublime and momentous of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:44247:13"/>
all. And ſuch (we know) is his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, it being the way in which he is to ſerve his God, and aſſure his bliſsful love and favour, and thereby ſecure the Everlaſting welfare and happineſs of his Soul.</p>
               <p>I ſhall only deſire Two things fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be conſidered in this caſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That God hath plainly told us, that there ever will be Errors in the world, and that no age ſhall want Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtors and deceivers to broach them, and endeavour to entrap people with them: This he hath reſolved (for wiſe ends) to permit ſtill to be.</p>
               <p>And can it then be ſuppoſed, that God ſhould not furniſh his ſervants with an Antidote againſt them? Can any think ſo unworthily of God, as to believe that he hath expoſed the belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of his Soul, and the objects of his tendereſt compaſſions and regards na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and wholly defenceleſs, without any thing to ſecure themſelves againſt theſe plagues? This were indeed to overact the ſavage cruelty of the <hi>Hirca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Tiger,</hi> and tranſcribe the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:44247:13"/>
of the ſilly <hi>Oſtrich,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 39.14.</note> which leaveth her Eggs in the Sand, expoſed to the foot of every Beaſt or Traveller, to be cruſhed at pleaſure: Nothing can well be thought of, that is really more inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and reflective upon Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence than this is.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God hath not only told us of theſe things, but cautioned us againſt them, and ſtrictly commanded us to beware of them, as is evident to any that conſults the holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Now can it enter into the hearts of men to believe, that God that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands this, ſhould not provide ſome way by which it might be done? I could never yet (though educated when ſuch doctrines were much in vogue) bring my thoughts quietly to believe that God would command utter impoſſibilities; which were far to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the cruelty of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Task-maſters, which himſelf hath condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ſo tragically declaimed againſt: And I no way doubt, but that if he have commanded us to prove all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44247:14"/>
things, to try the Spirits, to keep our ſelves from being infected with the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the wicked; that he hath alſo furniſhed us with power, and provided a means, how we may do all theſe things.</p>
               <p>God certainly never commands things in vain, nor will he tantalize the endeavours of his people, nor make himſelf ſport to illude the hopes and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of poor mortals, by putting them upon Acquiſts whoſe glories though they may excite, yet their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilities do diſcourage, and fruſtrate the moſt vigorous endeavours. And that man would have a ſtrange notion of God, that would fancy his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding us to take heed of being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and yet not direct us to means by which we might do ſo.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That this Rule is obvious and plain, and intended for the guidance and benefit of all men. <hi>Hereby know we,</hi> &amp;c. And certainly he intends not hereby only himſelf, or Apoſtles like himſelf, but all thoſe whom in <hi>verſe</hi> 1. he had exhorted to try the Spirits, and not preſently to believe every pretence
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:44247:14"/>
of it, which is equally the intereſt and duty of all men.</p>
               <p>It is true the Prieſts lips ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve knowledge, and 'tis well when they do, and in many caſes mighty prudent to ſeek the Law at his mouth, conſult him often in our doubts and difficulties, and not be too peremptory in our own concluſions.</p>
               <p>But yet I think no man can with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon believe, that God ever intended theſe to be the only Oracles, to which every Chriſtian ſhould repair and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent himſelf with the reſponſes of. I think, I could urge inconveniences againſt this, which the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave would be ſomething puzled to ſolve.</p>
               <p>As God hath endued every man with a Soul, and that Soul with an underſtanding, and that underſtanding with power of judging and diſcerning things that differ, and commanded eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man to be faithful to this Talent, and diligent in improving and encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his ſtock of light, that thereby he may be able to take the better heed he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:44247:15"/>
be not deceived: So doubtleſs he hath ſubſtituted a way by which every man may do this; and hath not intended the benefit of it to be confined only to ſome few particular perſons.</p>
               <p>It hath been long ſince objected, and deſigned to reproach the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that they are very plain, and content themſelves with familiar re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations of things, accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to vulgar capacities, and not fit to ſatisfie the enquiries and exerciſe the curioſity of deep ſpeculators, and ſubtil Philoſophers.</p>
               <p>And the truth of the objection hath been willingly granted (as to the main) and yet the honour and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of them for that reaſon vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and Gods goodneſs thereupon magnified and exalted, who foreſeeing that the greateſt part of his followers would not be great Clerks, and deep Scholars, but illiterate and plain men, hath mercifully conſulted their weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and complied with it, and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:44247:15"/>And he that conſiders that God va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues the Soul of one man, equally with anothers, and deſires equally the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of all, will preſently conclude, that therefore he hath conſulted the benefit of all men, and not ſet up a rule to judge truth by, which ſhould be mighty obſcure and intricate, and very few (only ſome learned men) ſhould be able to reap benefit from.</p>
               <p>Thus much therefore we have gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from this Text, both that God hath left us a way by which to know Truth from Error, and that this is ſuch a way as all men may improve, and make uſe of to the ſame end.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:44247:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Two ways propounded for the proof of the Aſſertion, Scripture and Reaſon. This Text improved largely to this purpoſe, and <hi>Matth. 7.16.</hi> of which a full Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication is endeavoured.</head>
               <p>HAving thus prepared the way to the proof of the forenamed Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the preceeding Chapter; I ſhall now addreſs directly to it in this. And two ways I ſhall endeavour to give ſtrength to the truth of it by:
<list>
                     <item>1. By Scripture.</item>
                     <item>2. By Reaſon and Argument, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by Scripture.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. I begin with the confirmation of this from holy Scripture, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is the chiefeſt way of proving this truth, and before all other things fit to determine this controverſie. For ſince we have reaſon with all due humility and gratitude to acknowledge this to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:44247:16"/>
be a full, ſufficient and perfect revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the will of God to man, in which all neceſſary directions to happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are contained, and whatever elſe is needful to make the man of God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, throughly furniſhed unto all good works,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.17.</note> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> warrants us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve: So if God have provided ſuch a way for men to judge Truth and Error by, he hath doubtleſs given ſome inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of it in theſe Divine Inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Records.</p>
               <p>Now what theſe ſpeak of this matter I ſhall endeavour to acquaint you. And firſt, as from this place of S. <hi>John</hi> I have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken occaſion to raiſe,<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 4.6.</note> ſo I ſhall now try what there is in it, to confirm the Aſſertion. Which that I may diſtinctly and clearly do, I muſt deſire you to read the precedent verſes, and conſider what the Apoſtle is deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in them. And that you will eaſily find to be this, an endeavour to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm thoſe he writes to, in the true faith of Chriſt, that they might not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:44247:17"/>
be drawn from it by any pretences, and particularly by thoſe great preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the Spirit, that were then ſo common amongſt all ſeducers, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> as indeed it hath been ordinary ever ſince almoſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all Hereticks that have infeſted the Church.</p>
               <p>This caution of not believing all theſe pretences he expreſly mentions <hi>verſe</hi> 1. and by an excellent Argument enforceth, becauſe there are many falſe Prophets are gone out into the world.</p>
               <p>Now in order to this trial and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the Spirits and the Doctrines iſſuing from them, he layeth down theſe three chief rules in the following diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>The firſt whereof is the free confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt, and faith in him in times of perſecution, the lawfulneſs and prudence of denying of whom, when trouble and danger threatned a man for ſo doing, was one of the great doctrines of the <hi>Gnoſticks:</hi> This he treats of <hi>verſe</hi> 2, 3. and then ſubjoyns a commendation of theſe Chriſtians,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:44247:17"/>
and congratulates with them, that they had avoided the infection of theſe falſe teachers, ſhewing withal, what had aſſiſted them to do ſo, and why they ſhould perſiſt in their care againſt them, <hi>verſe</hi> 4, 5.</p>
               <p>The ſecond rule is laid down in this Text; the intendment of which I ſhall preſently acquaint you more fully with.</p>
               <p>But becauſe this is general, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanceth thirdly in a particular of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian purity and obedience, <hi>viz.</hi> true charity to our Brethren, which he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts on in the following part of the Chapter.</p>
               <p>I am not concern'd to inſiſt upon ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the firſt or third rule ſo as largely to explain them, but chiefly upon the ſecond, for the enſuring of which, there needs but only the right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the word, <hi>Hear:</hi> He that is of God <hi>heareth</hi> us: And that by this expreſſion is intended, <hi>obeying,</hi> cannot ſeem ſtrange to any, that will remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that it is the common word by which obedience is generally expreſſed in the Sacred <hi>Idiom.</hi> The places in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:44247:18"/>
which it is thus uſed are too many to be named, and the commonneſs of the phraſe too great to need it.</p>
               <p>So that by <hi>hearing us,</hi> is meant obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our doctrine, which is of God (as he ſpeaks) <hi>i. e.</hi> pure and holy like its bleſſed Author, hath nothing of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly greatneſs, or ſecular intereſt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign in it; but only of piety, and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſelf-denial, and contempt of the world, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and this is an argument of its being truly Divine, and a Rule by which alſo to judge whatever do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is ſo, or the contrary. That doctrine that is truly of God, is all for holineſs, and obedience, and purity, while the other is for worldly advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and ſuited to common Intereſts, and hereby know we the Spirit of Truth and the Spirit of Error in all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of doctrines, <hi>i. e.</hi> all doctrines that are conducive to real holineſs, are of God, proceed from the Spirit of Truth, and every doctrine that inclines to the contrary doth certainly proceed from the Spirit of Error.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:44247:18"/>Now if you think that I am injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in referring thus the trial of Spirits and doctrines only to this one Rule, while I have told you before that S. <hi>John</hi> layeth down Two more in this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the ſame purpoſe; I ſhall readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſs the charge, but without any Imputation of injuſtice: yea, ſhall take advantage from hence the more to ſtrengthen this Aſſertion, and to lay down this as the chief and principal Rule, foraſmuch as both the others do relate to it, and are inſtances of it. For a free undaunted confeſſing of Chriſt in times of danger, and loving cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally our Brethren, are both of them chief branches of Chriſtian vertue and holineſs, and indeed as they are almoſt above all other things commanded by our Saviour, ſo they have the choiceſt and moſt endearing encouragements annexed to them.</p>
               <p>So then the Argument from this place will be very clear and concluding; for in that very place where S. <hi>John</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns the trial of Spirits and Doctrines, he layeth down this as the great Rule
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:44247:19"/>
for that trial, and though he add Two other Rules alſo, yet they are but par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars and branches of this great one. And then the whole of the Apoſtles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections in this caſe, amounts to thus much, Whatever doctrine doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to make men truly holy, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally encourageth to the right taking up the Croſs of Chriſt, and a cordial con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant love to our Brethren, that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine iſſueth from the Spirit of Truth; and whatever doctrine is contrary ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to theſe Two ſingle Chriſtian ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, or to it in general, doth certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proceed from the Spirit of Error: and this I take to be the natural and true purport of S. <hi>John</hi> in this Text.</p>
               <p>But I would not have you think that he is ſingular in this, or without good authority for what he ſaith, we ſhall find he had ſufficient warrant from his great Maſter Chriſt <hi>Jeſus,</hi> as we may clearly ſee, if we conſider that ſpeech of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.16, 20.</note> 
                  <hi>By their fruits ye ſhall know them.</hi> — In the preceding Verſes our Saviour is forewarning his Diſciples of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:44247:19"/>
the coming of falſe Prophets into the world, and of the very ſpecious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences that they ſhould make to deceive people by: Having done this and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd againſt them, he layeth down in this place a Rule to know and diſcover them by, which Rule is very poſitive and plain, and twice repeated, that we ſhould not doubt of it, or forget it. <hi>By their fruits ye ſhall know them; i. e.</hi> by the natural conſequences and fruits of their doctrines, by ſuch concluſions as do naturally and by right arguing follow from them.</p>
               <p>So that the trial of Prophets is to be made by trial of their doctrines, and theſe are to be tried by the natural con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences and effects of them: not by what a man can diſcover in the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors or venters of ſuch doctrines, for theſe many times are very cloſe and ſubtil Hypocrites, and lead their lives with very great heed and warineſs, wearing the Sheeps skin to conceal the Wolfs heart, and always putting on the form of godlineſs to cover their malicious and rotten deſigns, and no
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:44247:20"/>
wonder, for Satan can transform him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into an Angel of light: — but by the natural conſequences and effects of the doctrines.</p>
               <p>For otherwiſe it were almoſt utterly impoſſible to make a diſcovery of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines by this Rule, ſince all men do not live up exactly to the conſequences of their own Tenets. One man may have a right faith, and yet lead a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed life; and another may have a rotten falſe belief in ſome particulars, and yet be tolerably well in his life. And there is no doubt, but many a well-meaning man may embrace an Error in ſimplicity, without underſtanding rightly what the miſchievous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of it are, yea perhaps without ever practiſing thoſe conſequences. Men may be honeſt, and yet careleſs, and be impoſed upon, and ſo on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry too; but I ſhall ſay more to this hereafter.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, we may reſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied that our Saviour means by fruits, ſuch things as are the natural conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, and proper products of ſuch
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:44247:20"/>
doctrines: and this he clears and aſſures the truth and reaſonableneſs of, by an excellent and well known compariſon, and indeed it holds true both ways, men do not gather Grapes from Thorns, nor Figs from Thiſtles, nor do Vines yield the Berries of Thorns, nor doth the Doune of Thiſtles grow upon Fig-trees. For though it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible (and God knows too common too) for a man to detain the truth in unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18.</note> yet the unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs iſſues from the man, not from the truth. And though a Heretick may poſſibly be eminent in ſome good things, yet his heart is to be praiſed for it, not his head, <hi>i. e.</hi> his goodneſs is not the effect of his Error, nor upon any account at all aſcribable to it.</p>
               <p>So then if we keep us to our Saviours ſenſe, the Rule is true, and will never deceive us. Thoſe doctrines that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign nothing, but to make men pure and holy, and conſcientious, and ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly regardful of our Chriſtian duty, cannot but iſſue from the Spirit of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:44247:21"/>
Truth, and Satan can never be contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butive to a doctrine that tends ſo much to the overthrow of his deſign and great Intereſt in the world. But whatever doctrines or broachers of them, do any way infuſe into men, or encourage and prompt them to any Impiety, any Sin, let their ſhews be never ſo ſpecious, their pretences never ſo fair, yet thoſe Prophets are falſe Prophets, and thoſe doctrines fumes from Hell, whoſe great deſign it is to corrupt mens man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, debauch their lives, and keep them from the love and practice of piety.</p>
               <p>This is all that I have to offer from theſe Two places of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and truly I think what hath been offered, enough to confirm the Collection, and to gain the aſſent of every good Chriſtian to the truth of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:44247:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> The old Teſtament cited alſo for the proof of this, and two great conſiderations added to give more Evidence to it. This the rule to try Prophets by of old, and the beſt Criterion of a true Divine Miracle.</head>
               <p>THE former Chapter having ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted you with ſome proofs for this out of the New Teſtament, I ſhall proceed to add ſome to them alſo out of the Old: For this is no new thing, nor unknown to the <hi>Jews</hi> in time of old, but it was deliver'd to them alſo, as the great Rule to judge by in this caſe: of which I take that place of the Prophet to be clear evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; <hi>To the Law and to the Teſtimony,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 8.20.</note> 
                  <hi>and if they ſpeak not according to this Rule, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</hi> In the preceding Verſes the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:44247:22"/>
Prophet is inveighing againſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning the attending to any extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary pretenders to knowledge or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations, ſuch as Wizards and Necro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancers, and thoſe that conſulted fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar Spirits: And in this Verſe he layeth down a Rule by which to try all revelations and pretences of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; bring them to the <hi>Law</hi> and to the <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> and if in any thing they differ from that, then there is no morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or light in them, but they ariſe out of the infernal <hi>ſpecus,</hi> and are ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Spirit and Prince of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>This ſeems to me to be very clear, and yet I ſhall add ſomething more, that this was not only appointed to be the Rule of judging in all ordinary dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences about, doctrines, but in the moſt extraordinary alſo that could poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly happen. I ſhall inſtance in Two that were the chiefeſt of all, — pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions to Prophecy and working of Miracles.</p>
               <p>Theſe were indeed extraordinary ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and therefore, though the judging
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:44247:22"/>
of them did not belong to every private man, but only to the great Sanhedrim, (as learned men have clearly proved) yet it will be very much to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, if we can prove that even this great Conſiſtory was to judge by this Rule, of the Truth or Falſhood of both of them.</p>
               <p>And firſt for Prophets, I think the caſe is ſufficiently clear from that place of <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 13. from <hi>verſe</hi> 1, to 6. from which (if you read and conſider it well) you will be able to make this Collection, that neither the predicting of a future Event, no nor the coming of that to paſs according to the predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, are ſafe and warrantable things to judge a Prophet by: for if that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet entice any way to Idolatry, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver any thing that may draw them away from their duty, in walking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Lord, and fearing him, and keeping his Commandments, and obeying his voice, he is to be rejected, yea to be ſtoned as an Impoſtor, and a deceiver. So that the truth of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and the divinity of his prophecy
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:44247:23"/>
was to be judged only (or at leaſt chiefly) by the conſonancy thereof to the Law of God.</p>
               <p>This is a thing that I judge worth our taking notice of at this time: Alas, if the bold pretenders to prophecy in this Age could make this plea for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that things fall out exactly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their predictions, what a great noiſe would they ſoon make? how mightily would they boaſt? and plead (and perhaps believe too) them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be true Prophets? And yet God himſelf tells us, this is no ſafe and ſure Rule to judge men true Prophets by.</p>
               <p>For the Spirit of Error may poſſibly predict many things, and the Events anſwer the predictions, and many times we know it hath been thus. And we do not know how far the skill of the Devil may extend in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>Beſides, God hath told us, that he many times permits ſuch things to come to paſs, that he may thereby try the love and fidelity of men: Cauſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:44247:23"/>
theſe to be a puniſhment unto all thoſe that are unreaſonably fickle and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and on the other hand, that (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks in caſe of Hereſies) thoſe that are cordial and approved may be made known.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I know there are many Rules laid down by the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Rabbies, and others after them for the trial of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and a great ſtir made about them: But he that will conſiderately read them over, as he will find this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways mentioned as one Rule, ſo he will find that it is the chiefeſt and ſafeſt, and that to which all at laſt are forced to flee.</p>
               <p>The Second caſe that I choſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in was the caſe of Miracles: for that there are true and lying won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, the Scripture clearly aſſures us. But how to diſtinguiſh betwixt theſe, is really a very great and perplexing difficulty, and ſome men have taken a great deal of pains to give directions herein: And indeed muſt do ſo ſtill, until they come to fix and reſt upon this.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:44247:24"/>For when all is done, this certainly is the eaſieſt and ſafeſt too, namely, to conſider what the effects and deſigns of them are, if they have Divine effects upon men, eſpecially if they only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to make men holy and good, or to atteſt a doctrine that teacheth men how to be ſo; then they carry the cleareſt ſtamp of Divinity upon them that can be: but if they tend in any meaſure to the contrary, either to encourage men in ſin, or atteſt any doctrine, that teacheth any thing contrary to the holy Law and Precepts of God, then they are to be ſuſpected and rejected as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate effects of the Spirit of deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:44247:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> A further diſcourſe of Miracles, and of their Evidence, and how to know which are Divine, and which not. An addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all from the Nature of Hereſie, and wherein the Notion of it doth chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſiſt.</head>
               <p>BUT this Sir, may perhaps by you be thought too little to be ſaid on this great ſubject of Miracles; for the whole World doth look upon them to be Divine Teſtimonies, ſufficient Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of truth, and able to aſſure the verity, gain aſſent to, and entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any doctrine that they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to atteſt. The Chriſtian Church in all Ages hath ſpoken great things of them, and gloried in them, and argued (with great aſſurance) the Divinity and Truth of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion from them. And he would certainly do a great diſſervice to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:44247:25"/>
that ſhould go about in any meaſure to weaken the teſtimony of them.</p>
               <p>And therefore Sir, that I may not ſuffer under any of theſe prejudices, I ſhall a little further enlarge this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of them, and what I have to ſay, that it may be diſtinct and plain, ſhall be contained in theſe ſubſequent propoſitions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I do moſt readily grant, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially believe that <hi>Divine</hi> Miracles are certain Evidences of Truth: For it is no way reaſonable to ſuppoſe, that God ſhould annex his Seal to atteſt any thing that is untrue. Whatever God aſſerts, muſt needs for that very reaſon be true, were there none elſe; and all the World is agreed in their belief of this. So that I take it, Miracles are not added to confirm the truth of what God hath declared, but rather to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince men that he doth declare ſuch things, or to atteſt the Divine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of thoſe that are his Inſtruments therein.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:44247:25"/>2. But then ſecondly, I do as aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly believe that they are not the only Evidences of truth. A Divine do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine may carry in it many things, that may be as clear ſignatures, and ought to be as convincing characters of Truth, as immediate Miracles are. This may in ſome meaſure be collected from that parabolical diſcourſe of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> to the rich man in Hell:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 16.31.</note> 
                  <hi>If they believe not Moſes and the Prophets, neither will they believe though one roſe from the dead.</hi> Intimating that thoſe doctrines in <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Prophetick writings, had as much Evidence of Truth, and as clear Convictions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in them, as the miraculous appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of one from the dead could give to them.</p>
               <p>But there is a clearer place in the Goſpel to aſſure this upon, for our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour doth in one place, <hi>viz. John</hi> 15.22. as much aggravate the guilt of the <hi>Jews</hi> Infidelity, in not believing his heavenly pure doctrine, as he doth in another, <hi>viz. verſe</hi> the 24. of the ſame
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:44247:26"/>
Chapter: For their not believing the unparalell'd Miracles which he did among them, which certainly he would never have done, but that the Evidences and Convictions of truth were equal in both.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But then thirdly, I add that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Miracle is not an unqueſtionable Evidence of truth, nor a ſufficient warrant for men preſently to believe upon its ſole account: All the world, I think, is agreed about this alſo: For all men unanimouſly believe that only true and really Divine Miracles are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to aſſure the credibility of things. And all Miracles are not ſo; for there are lying wonders as well as true, and it is not ſafe to believe equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in both caſes.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And therefore fourthly, there is an abſolute neceſſity, that a man be aſſured the Miracle is truly Divine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he can ſafely believe upon the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority thereof; otherwiſe he may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the lying wonder as well as the other, and believe what <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> ſay as well as <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:44247:26"/>5. It is ſo very difficult, that it is almoſt next to impoſſible, by any thing immediately in the Miracles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to know which is truly Divine, and which is not ſo: I ſay in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles themſelves: I mean they do not carry ſuch ſignatures upon them, that a man by them only, can eaſily make a judgment.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I have no reaſon to doubt, but that evil Spirits by God's permiſſion, may effect things that are truly miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, or if you require it plainly, true Miracles. For my part, I do not ſee any reaſon, why the ſame things done by the forenamed Sorcerers, were not as true Miracles, as when done by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and it will be hard for any man to ſhew a difference. If the turning a Rod into a Serpent was a Miracle, they did it as well as <hi>Moſes.</hi> If converting water into bloud was a Miracle, it was ſo when done by them, as well as when done by <hi>Moſes:</hi> and though it be true, that <hi>Moſes</hi> did ſome Miracles, which they could not, yet that relieves us little; for though they did not all Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:44247:27"/>
which he did, yet they did ſome. So that ſtill they wrought true Miracles as well as <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Nor ſecondly, ſhall men be relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by ſaying ſome are lying wonders and ſome are true: For it is probable, thoſe wonders are called lying won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, not becauſe they were not really wonders (or Miracles, for the word ſignifieth equally both) but becauſe they were deſigned to atteſt an untruth, a lie: For ſo the <hi>Greek</hi> ſeems eſpecially to mean,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.9.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, miracles or won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of falſhood, as our own Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors put it in the Margent; and ſo the learned <hi>Grotius</hi> expounds it, and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the Expoſition by a known truth, <hi>Nam quod vice genitivi eſt apud Hebreos, ſaepe finem ſignificat:</hi> where you have a Learned diſcourſe to the purpoſe I am now upon. And <hi>Beza</hi> alſo expounds it to the ſame pupoſe too, <hi>Mendacii ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliendi cauſâ edita, Wonders wrought on purpoſe to confirm a lie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Nor thirdly, will it any more help us to grant that ſome are lying
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:44247:27"/>
wonders in the other ſence, unleſs we could certainly tell which were ſo. Whether the wonder be real or no, it is all one to me, unleſs I be able to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh betwixt them. Suppoſe thoſe of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Sorcerers, or <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> or <hi>Apollonius Tyaneus</hi> (whom the Heathens ſet up to vye with Chriſt) I ſay ſuppoſe theſe were not real Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, but preſtigious and deluſive, yet how ſhall any man know, and make it appear they were ſo? they are as Convictive as true ones, unleſs they could be plainly diſcovered not to be ſo: and how to do this (from any thing in the things themſelves) I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs my ſelf wholly ignorant.</p>
               <p n="4">4. For fourthly, I ſhall receive little ſatisfaction by what is commonly ſaid in this caſe, that's a true Miracle which can only be effected by a Divine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: for ſuppoſe that were granted true, yet how ſhall I know what can only be effected ſo, and what not? No man knows the limits of Satan's power, nor can ſay hitherto can he go, and no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, unleſs he can tell more than ever
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:44247:28"/>
man yet did: nay perhaps no man can exactly tell the utmoſt reach of natural power, or define preciſely how far na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural cauſes when rightly applied, can work. And if he know not this, he knows little in order to ſatisfaction in this matter.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Nor truly is there much more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief in flying to the evident greatneſs of Miracles; though I gladly confeſs there is ſomething in it; and it ought to be adored as a ſignal act of Divine Providence, that <hi>Moſes,</hi> and eſpecially Chriſt herein have the eminency above any other pretenders to Miracles in the world: for <hi>Moſes</hi> his Rod ſwallowed up the Magician's Rods, and <hi>Apolloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> could not heal all diſeaſes, as Chriſt did, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſtill this is ſhort of fully relieving us; for perhaps ſome things may ſeem greater Miracles to us, which are not ſo indeed. And ſubtil wits would ſay many things, to make it ſeem at leaſt, that all Miracles are equally great.</p>
               <p>And ſuppoſe it to be ſo, that many people might ſee ſome of theſe Miracles
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:44247:28"/>
only, and not the other: As ſuppoſe the <hi>Samaritans</hi> that ſaw the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> did not ſee thoſe of Chriſt, or the Apoſtles, nor thoſe that ſaw the wonders of <hi>Apollonius,</hi> to have heard of the other. I ask now what they ſhould do in this caſe? If a Miracle be a good ground of truth, then they had that warrant to believe as grand falſhoods as ever were in the world.</p>
               <p>But further yet, if you look into the Goſpel, you ſhall find Chriſt telling his Apoſtles,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.24.</note> that the falſe Chriſts that ſhould ariſe after him, ſhould ſhew, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, great ſigns and wonders; and ſo great, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the very Elect, were they not mightily aſſiſted to avoid that decepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p n="6">6. From all which I collect that a bare Miracle is not enough to aſſure the truth, and warrant the belief of every Doctrine atteſted by it: for then the doctrine of <hi>Apollonius</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus</hi> had the ſame credibility as that of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:44247:29"/>
Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.14.</note> And if you look into the Revelations of S. <hi>John,</hi> you ſhall find mention of a Beaſt which deceived men by Miracles which he had power to do: And in another <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.14.</note> place we read of the Spirits of Devils going forth to work Miracles: and <note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 19.20.</note> again of a falſe Prophet that wrought Miracles. If Miracles there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore warrant Faith of every Doctrine, then they do alſo warrant that of the Devil and his Spirits, which God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Upon the ſtrength of all which Conſiderations, I ſay that Miracles themſelves need ſomething to atteſt them, and ſhew men when they are to believe them, and when not to do ſo; and I miſtake much, if what hath been ſaid do not make this apparent.</p>
               <p n="8">8. And therefore laſtly, to bring all to a final iſſue, I do not know any thing ſo certain a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of a Miracle, as the end and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of it. If the doctrine that it is
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:44247:29"/>
wrought to atteſt, be plainly pure and holy, a myſtery indeed of Godlineſs, and the effects that it produceth in men be anſwerable, <hi>i. e.</hi> the bringing them off from Idolatry and wickedneſs, to live religious and holy lives.</p>
               <p>And upon theſe Two accounts eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, we ſhall find <hi>Origen</hi> and moſt of the firſt Apologiſts, proving the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of our Saviours Miracles, and arguing the Miracles boaſted by the Heathen, to be Helliſh and Diabolical, becauſe they were all done, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Origen</hi> ſpeaks, to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivableneſs of unrighteouſneſs, and to draw men into Idolatry, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of filthineſs.</p>
               <p>And truly (for my own part) I do not know, upon what any man can ſafely reſt in this matter, but upon this. The deſign and effect of Miracles is the beſt <hi>Index</hi> of them. Where a doctrine, upon due ſearch, is truly divine and holy, and contrived to no other end, but to make all men ſo, and Miracles wrought by the promulgers of it, to atteſt the Divinity of their Doctrine
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:44247:30"/>
and Miſſion; there is doubtleſs all (the moſt unqueſtionable) evidence of truth, that even God himſelf is able to give.</p>
               <p>So that the holineſs of a Doctrine, proves the Divinity of the Miracle, as well as the Divinity of the Miracle at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts the truth of the Doctrine.</p>
               <p>And this is founded upon this moſt certain reaſon, that the Devil is a hater of goodneſs, and therefore will never effect any thing, to encourage or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote it amongſt men: All his Intereſt lieth another way, and his kingdom is ſupported by ſin and wickedneſs.</p>
               <p>But God is a lover of holineſs, it is his own very Life and Image; and as all his works of Providence are intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the good of Souls, ſo all his works of wonder eſpecially are deſigned to make men holy, and therefore ſhall never atteſt any doctrine but what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth to that great purpoſe.</p>
               <p>I have now Sir, no more to add on this great ſubject, but only to ſhew you, that I am not ſingular in this No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: if you will pleaſe to be at the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:44247:30"/>
trouble of reading any the large diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Rabbies on this ſubject, you ſhall find this to be the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſolid thing to be ſafely relied upon, and indeed that upon which they are forced at laſt to rely chiefly upon.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall mention to you two au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, which I am apt to think, will ſignifie as much with you as the whole Sanhedrim. The Learned <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> and the little leſs Learned Doctor <hi>Stillingfleet;</hi> if you read the Notes of the firſt upon 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.9. you will find his opinion to be exactly conſonant to what I have been propoſing. And if you'l pleaſe to remember (what I know you have read) the Ninth and Tenth Chapters of the Dean's <hi>Origines Sacrae,</hi> (in the latter of which he ſaith as much to diſtinguiſh true Divine Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles from falſe, as I think the matter can poſſibly bear) you will find, that though he lay down other marks, and certainly ſay as much upon them as ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally can be ſaid, yet truly there's but little to fix contentedly and with ſatisfaction upon, in any other, but
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:44247:31"/>
theſe Two, <hi>viz.</hi> the nature and deſign of the Doctrine they do atteſt, and the effects they produce in the minds of men.</p>
               <p>And now Sir, before I put a period to this Chapter, I ſhall (and I do not well know where better) add another Conſideration, of ſome moment to ſtrengthen our preſent Aſſertion: And that is from the conſideration of the true notion of Hereſie. For if the great Rule to judge this thing by, be holineſs alſo, then I think it will be another good addition to our preſent Argument.</p>
               <p>I conſider then that as Hereſie is marked in holy Scripture as a very great ſin, and as ſeverely characterized as any other ſin whatſoever; ſo the chief reaſon why it is ſo, is becauſe it is in ſome meaſure or other a receſſion from the holineſs, and from that faith that is the foundation and ſupport of it.</p>
               <p>For therefore are Hereticks called men of corrupt minds, Reprobates con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerning the faith, Enemies to God,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:44247:31"/>
and Antichriſts, all which characters do denote not their Error ſo much in matters of Faith, as in practice, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply their ſeceſſions chiefly from the rules of holineſs.</p>
               <p>And the truth is, according to the ſenſe of the beſt Antiquity, men do ſo far depart from the faith, as they do from holineſs, and they are Hereticks not for that, but eſpecially for this.</p>
               <p>I do very well know how much men are alter'd now in their conceits about Hereſie, from what they were of old: And the multiplying Articles; of faith, and adopting Explications of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Creeds, is too clear an evidence of it, ſome men making theſe things advantages upon which to condemn for Hereſie preſently whatever in any thing differs from them.</p>
               <p>But Sir, theſe things move me very little, unleſs it be to lament, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſerate the uncharitableneſs of men in this matter.</p>
               <p>He that would have a right notion of Hereſie, muſt ſearch what the Apoſtles, and Apoſtolick Ages called
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:44247:32"/>
by that name, and not preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach as Hereſie every thing that dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers from him. And whoever will do ſo, will find that Hereſie is Hereſie, becauſe it is a work of the fleſh, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a wicked opinion, and an ungodly doctrine, an error <hi>in materiâ practicâ,</hi> in practice not in opinion only, ſomething that was amiſs <hi>in genere morum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For Faith is called by S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.3.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a doctrine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Godlineſs; and thoſe that are Hereticks, are called unjuſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, uncharitable, perjured perſons, and for that reaſon are ſaid to oppoſe ſound doctrine.</p>
               <p>And that this only is the true notion of Hereſie, may be made further to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, from theſe Two primitive and Scriptural obſervations.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The conſidering thoſe perſons and doctrines that were branded with that ill character by the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Their carriage towards the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Converts in the great matter of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:44247:32"/>
and the Law of Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Of the Firſt, you will find in the Apoſtles times but a very few, nor in the Age immediately ſucceeding: Some tell us not above ſeven, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them Hereticks for this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, becauſe they taught practical Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties, or denied ſuch Articles in the Creed, upon which the neceſſity of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs was founded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Simon Magus</hi> taught monſtrous things of the Holy Ghoſt, and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous things of himſelf. <hi>Ebion</hi> and <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthus</hi> denied the Divinity of Chriſt, enjoyned the obſervation of the <hi>Moſaick</hi> Law, and allowed uncleanneſs, and had impious Theorems about luſt.</p>
               <p>And the ſame is as true of <hi>Menander Baſilides, Carpocrates,</hi> &amp;c. whoſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions were therefore judg'd Heretical, not ſo much becauſe they were real un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths, as becauſe they were open de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiances to all Faith, Sobriety and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If you conſider the Apoſtles car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage towards the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Converts,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:44247:33"/>
you will ſoon perceive how far they were from cenſuring any errors pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently for Hereſies, if they maintained the neceſſity of holineſs and a good life.</p>
               <p>For you will ſcarcely be able to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in a doctrine more truly contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Chriſtian Faith, and the whole purport of the Goſpel, than that of thoſe <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Converts was, which thought it abſolutely neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to obſerve, the Ancient Rites, and as S. <hi>James</hi> informs S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 21.20.</note> were all zealous of the Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet we know theſe were always tolerated, no ill characters fixed upon them, fellowſhip always allowed them, indulged and permitted to their error, which laſted among them for the time of fifteen Chriſtian Biſhops, who were all Circumciſed, yea till the final de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the City and Temple, and all, under <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperor, and long afterwards.</p>
               <p>And this was the reaſon we know of the Apoſtolick Canons in that firſt
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:44247:33"/>
great Council, which were all contrived in favour to them, and counted neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary only in order to the avoiding ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal to them, as was alſo the obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſeventh day Sabbath for ſome Centuries of years, only for the ſame reaſon.</p>
               <p>From whence we may ſafely collect thus much, that in thoſe beſt and moſt charitable of times, no man was count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an Heretick that did erre <hi>bonâ mente,</hi> and retain'd a neceſſity of holineſs, and a belief of the great grounds upon which that neceſſity was founded.</p>
               <p>And now Sir, this Addition will not be impertinent to our purpoſe; for all Heretical doctrines are ſome way or other contrary unto holineſs, and their being this is the reaſon of their being the other, and while they are not one, we ought by no means to call them the other, unleſs we will imitate the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe men, who can indure none (no not the leaſt) diſſenting in opinion from them in any thing, under any kinder character than Hereſie. So that he that maintained the being of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:44247:34"/>
                  <hi>Antipodes</hi> was like to be branded once with that name, and <hi>Galileo</hi> hardly eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped the ſame character for maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Copernican hypotheſis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But Sir, if you deſire to ſee this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Hereſie more fully diſcourſed, I refer you to a place in Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s Works, where it is inſiſted on at large, with that plainneſs and candor, and ſtrength of reaſon that is ſo common and uſual to that moſt excellent man; it is his <hi>Liberty of Propheſying,</hi> a good Book under an ill name. But truly I know not for what reaſon, unleſs it were for endeavouring by much truth, to aſſwage and mitigate the raſh zeal, and unjuſt ſeverity of the late times againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and all that adhered unto her.</p>
               <p>From whence whoever takes liberty to traduce that great man as an allower of all Opinions, and any Medley in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, will be very unjuſt, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim himſelf either ignorant or unob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervant of his deſign, which though it be to gain favour to ſome ſpeculative Opinions, yet no man reflects more
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:44247:34"/>
ſeverely upon all that contradict holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and a good life, and are vented to the diſorder and diſturbance of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment either of the Kingdom or Church.</p>
               <p>And therefore I do not well ſee what diſſervice it can do that Church which is far enough from imperiouſly impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon the Conſciences of men, and rigorous tying them up to exact com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with it in all doctrines, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows (as all Churches muſt whether they will or no) a liberty to mens thoughts, provided they reſerve them to themſelves, and vent them not in order to Schiſm and Faction.</p>
               <p>But whether it be thus or not, is not my buſineſs to determine, much leſs becoming me to undertake to reach thoſe above me what to ſay or think: but this I freely ſay, I have ſo great an honour for the name of Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> that I would not willingly have any ill thing to blot his memory, and would do more than this (were it in my pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) to cauſe it might not.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:44247:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The Arguments from reaſon for the proof of the Collection: Four of theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded; and Two inſiſted on in this Chapter: The firſt taken from the ends of theſe Two Spirits in the World: The ſecond from the great deſign of Chriſtian Religion.</head>
               <p>AND now I am at liberty to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance to the Second way I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed for the proof of this Aſſertion; and that is from Reaſon and Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and there are Four of theſe I ſhall chuſe to inſiſt on; not that I think them the only ones we have in this matter, but ſo ſufficient that they may ſuperſede all need of others.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt ſhall be taken from the conſideration of the different ends and deſigns of theſe two Spirits in the World.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:44247:35"/>2. The ſecond from the great end and deſign of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third from the inconvenience of ſubſtituting any other Rule beſides this in this caſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. From the manifeſt advantage of this above any other, that can be ſo ſubſtituted.</p>
               <p>Theſe Four things will give aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance enough to this truth, and make it very evident.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I begin with the firſt, which is taken from the conſideration of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns that theſe two Spirits have in the World: The ſtrength of which argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to our preſent purpoſe will diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it ſelf in theſe two or three conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quential notices.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, As theſe are directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to each other, ſo they muſt needs be ſuppoſed to intend, and drive on dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent aims and deſigns in the World. The Spirit of truth is the Spirit of God, the Spirit of error is the Spirit of the Devil: And when light and darkneſs are reconciled each to other, when Chriſt and <hi>Belial</hi> become friends, then
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:44247:36"/>
may we ſuppoſe theſe Two Spirits to conſent, and agree together in the fame deſigns, but not before. There is no communion (ſaith the Apoſtle) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14.</note> nothing that's in common, nothing that's mutually ſhared betwixt light and darkneſs: But as ſoon as one appears, the other preſently flies away, as when the rayes of the morning diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover themſelves, the dark ſhades run away, and hide themſelves on the other ſide of this Globe: And ſo it is with theſe two Spirits, they are inconſiſtent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſite, and contrary each to other, and can never be any more reconciled in their deſigns, than they are in their natures: But thoſe will ſtill be as diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent as theſe are, as we ſee it ſtill to be in all other things, whoſe natures are contrary each to other.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, all the doctrines that iſſue from, or are ſuggeſted to men by theſe two Spirits, muſt needs be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be directed to theſe different ends, and deſigned on purpoſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the ſame. To ſuppoſe otherwiſe,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:44247:36"/>
were to imagine them falſe to their own Intereſts, and neglectful of them, or at leaſt dull and ſhort-ſighted, and unable to chuſe or pitch upon proper means for the promoting of the ſame; when no man hath any reaſon to imagine ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe things: For the Spirit of God is both Omniſcient and Active, and can never fail either to know what doctrines will beſt comport with its great deſign among men, or to purſue, and reveal thoſe doctrines to men, when it hath pitched on them. And he that will conſider how very ſubtil a Spirit the Devil is, and how unweari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly reſtleſs in managing his own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns in the world, can neither think him ignorant and unable to pitch upon ſuch doctrines as are conducive to that deſign, nor ſlow and backward to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude the belief of them upon men.</p>
               <p>He that thinks otherwiſe of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of truth, thinks very unbecomingly of God, and, as much as in him lies, precludes the way to his own welfare and ſafety, and deprives himſelf of that comfort, which would iſſue from the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:44247:37"/>
hearty belief of the Omniſcience, and Providence, and Watchfulneſs of the Spirit of truth for his good. And he that thinks otherwiſe of the Spirit of Error, and looks upon the Devil ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as a dull and unactive, or a ſilly and ignorant Spirit, is imprudent and injurious to himſelf, in undervaluing that Enemy, againſt whoſe ſubtilty and ſtrength, his utmoſt endeavours will be little enough. He is called a Lion for his ſtrength, and an old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent for his ſubtilty, and his reſtleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to execute the effects of both, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him juſtly formidable.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, the great ends of theſe two Spirits in the world are only theſe, to make men really and truly holy, and to make them really impure and vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. The firſt is the great deſign of the Spirit of Truth, this latter of the Spirit of Error. The firſt the Spirit of Truth intends, as the only way to make men happy. The ſecond the Devil mainly intends as the ſure way to render them Eternally miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:44247:37"/>There needs not much be ſaid on this branch of our Argument, the Scriptures are copious in atteſting the truth of it on both hands. The great work of the Spirit in the O.T. was to ſtrive with man, as is intimated by <hi>Moſes, Gen.</hi> 6.3. <hi>i. e.</hi> to withdraw him from ſin, and to induce him to the love and practice of vertue. And the ſame is the end he is ſent for in the New, to convince men of the evil of ſin, of the gain of righteouſneſs, and (as a means to both) to aſſure them of the certainty of Judgment:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 16.18.</note> and for this reaſon is called the Spirit of holineſs often, not only becauſe he is eſſentially and eminently ſo himſelf, but likewiſe becauſe his main buſineſs is to teach and encourage men to be ſo too, and to aſſiſt them in being faithful to thoſe encouragements and teachings.</p>
               <p>And then on the other hand, as it aſſures us that the firſt ſin of man owed it ſelf to the temptation and ſuggeſtion of the Devil, ſo it aſſures us that all his endeavour ever ſince hath been to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:44247:38"/>
heighten that ſin, and to promote the love and practice of wickedneſs among men. For this reaſon he is frequently called the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the wicked one, not only upon the account of his own wickedneſs, but for his ſtriving perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually to propagate that wickedneſs, by drawing men into all the ſad inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of it: And for the ſame reaſon he is called The Enemy, and the effects of his Enmity chiefly diſcover themſelves in this, the endeavouring to make men wicked like himſelf, and ſo to bring on them a portion of thoſe torments that are reſerved for himſelf, and for all thoſe mad Sons of men that are wicked as he is.</p>
               <p>And whoſoever obſerves his actings as they are recorded in the Scripture, or will but conſult the ſtories of his dealing with the Heathen world, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine but the doctrines which he taught them, and the rites and modes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that he inſtituted among them, will clearly ſee how all thoſe doctrines tended to ſin, and how the whole body of the Heathen worſhip, was indeed
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:44247:38"/>
what the Apoſtle calls it, a myſtery of wickedneſs.</p>
               <p>Now from theſe things the ſtrength of the argument will diſcover it ſelf. For ſince all the deſign of the Spirit of truth is to make men holy, to guide them into all truth, that it may thereby lead them to all goodneſs: And ſince the Spirit of error deſigns directly the contrary: And ſince all the doctrines that iſſue from theſe, are directed only to theſe great ends: It muſt needs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that whatever doctrine tends to holineſs muſt needs iſſue from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth: And whatever tends to the contrary, muſt needs proceed from the Spirit of Error. And that this is a ſure and ſafe way to judge whence they proceed by. For theſe two Spirits will ever be true to their own purpoſes and intereſts, and will always have an eye to the promoting of them, in all the doctrines that they propoſe to the Faith of men.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Another Argument may be drawn from the great end and deſign of Chriſtian Religion. For if we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:44247:39"/>
the author thereof prudent and wiſe, every doctrine therein will be ſo contrived, as to comport with, and promote the great aim of the whole; otherwiſe he would in effect pull down with one hand, what he endeavoured to build with the other.</p>
               <p>Now he that will conſider and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine this Religion with that ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and impartiality that things of this nature may juſtly expect, and chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge from all men, will ſoon find that it is indeed what S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>a myſtery of godlineſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Author of it, the ever bleſſed <hi>Jeſus,</hi> was indeed the Lamb of God, for his ſpotleſs innocency, as well as other reaſons.</p>
               <p>A perfect pattern of all holineſs and vertue. A divine perſon whoſe life was never ſullied with the leaſt of thoſe crimes, which ſo horribly ſtained the lives of the Heathen Deities. Whoſe innocency approved it ſelf ſo clearly to his very Judge, as to extort from him this confeſſion, that he was a
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:44247:39"/>
juſt perſon.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.24.</note> Yea that moſt Envious and Critical ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver, as well as Virulent accuſer of good men, could find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing whereof to accuſe the bleſſed <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: The Prince of this world cometh and findeth nothing in me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if you look into the Religion that he inſtituted in the world, you will ſoon find how exactly it reſembles and bears the lineaments of its holy Author, in all the parts of it. All its precepts and commands are ſo many injunctions of all the inſtances of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or prohibitions of the contrary inſtances of wickedneſs and vice. All its promiſes are great encouragements to induce men to comply with the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of thoſe commands: And its threatnings are added only to deter and affright them from all neglect and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the ſame.</p>
               <p>And ſhould we ſurvey the Articles of its Faith, and the doctrines that it propoſeth to the belief of men we ſhould ſoon find how mighty wiſely they are all contrived to promote the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:44247:40"/>
ſame great end. Even thoſe that ſeem moſtly ſpeculative and irrelative to du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet upon a cloſer view, will be found to be excellently conducive to it.</p>
               <p>For this is one honour juſtly due to Chriſtian Religion, that it doth not propoſe any uſeleſs Theorems, nor any dry and unprofitable ſpeculations to its votaries, but only require of them the faith and knowledge of things which are mighty uſeful, and greatly condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive to the real advantages of life and godlineſs. And this Sir, may perhaps be made appear hereafter in a diſtinct conſideration of all thoſe Articles of Faith, and particulars of Chriſtian doctrine, that have been moſtly excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt in this matter.</p>
               <p>At preſent I content my ſelf only in generals, and to add that this Truth is ſo very plain, and ſo fully illuſtrated, and ſubſtantially proved by many Learned men, not only thoſe Ancient Heroes, and worthy Apologiſts for Chriſtianity, but even ſome later wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and good men of our own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:44247:40"/>
that I think it needleſs to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt further upon it, but only to inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, that you may boldly defie any objections againſt it, and challenge the whole world either to inſtance in any one particular of it, that tolerates or encourageth any manner of vice, or to produce any other way of Religion, that ſo ſtrictly and univerſally enjoyns and promotes holineſs.</p>
               <p>And if this be ſo, we may very ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from hence alſo draw an Argument, for the proof of our preſent Aſſertion: For if the Chriſtian Religion be deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only to this great end, then what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever doctrine is truly and genuinely Chriſtian doth certainly comply with it, and ſome way or other promote the ſame. And whatever doctrine fails to do this, and is in any degree or inſtance repugnant hereunto, is certainly An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian; and we have warrant enough to reject it, as dictated by that Spirit of Error, which is certainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Spirit of Chriſtianity and Truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:44247:41"/>For (as I ſaid before) ſuppoſing the bleſſed Author of this Religion to be wiſe and prudent as God, and to have intended hereby only to make men ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it cannot reaſonably be ſuppoſed, that any doctrine which he hath delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red therein, ſhould not be conducive to that great deſign; for otherwiſe he would fruſtrate that by ſome doctrines, which he did endeavour to promote by others; which were a thing ſo very unbecoming a wiſe man, that it would be blaſphemy to affirm it of the Son of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The third and fourth Arguments propoſed: The Inconvenience of ſubſtituting any other rule but this, and the manifeſt advantage of this above any other that can be ſo ſubſtituted.</head>
               <p>THE laſt Chapter hath acquainted us with two Arguments, upon the ſtrength of which, I think, we may
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:44247:41"/>
ſafely conclude, that this is one ſure and certain rule to judge doctrines that pretend to be Chriſtian by. I ſhall now proceed to two other Arguments, whoſe deſign it is to make this rule ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear the beſt and ſafeſt to judge by.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And the form of them is taken from the manifeſt inconvenience of ſubſtituting any other rule to judge by in this caſe. I ſhall name thoſe that are moſt plauſibly contended for, and ſhew you the inconveniences that all of them are ſubject unto.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I begin with that which is the beſt and likelieſt of all, the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: And I do not intend by any thing I ſhall ſay in this diſcourſe, to derogate in the leaſt either from the authority or perfection of them. And I readily and thankfully grant theſe two things, which will ſufficiently ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure me from ſuch an imputation.</p>
               <p>Firſt, if men were honeſt and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere as they ſhould be, this rule would ſufficiently ſuperſede all need of any other, becauſe it is a perfect revelation of God's will, in which all things that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:44247:42"/>
are abſolutely needful to be believed, are fully contained, and intelligibly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered and expreſſed; and nothing but perverſeneſs and deſign can perplex them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, if men deſire to know what holineſs and vertue is, and to be directed in the inſtances of their duty: then the holy Scripture will fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie them: And if men honeſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult theſe, none but the obſtinate, and ſuch as deſign to cheat themſelves, can miſtake their directions.</p>
               <p>But ſtill after all this, I ſay we I are ſo unhappy as to ſee that holy Scripture doth not put an end to all controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies: We live in a Church that allows us theſe in the faireſt tranſlations, and plaineſt expoſitions, and not only al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows but enjoyns us the peruſal of them; and thinks it hath Divine war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to recommend to men the ſearching of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 5.39.</note> And therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits men to their plain duty, againſt which it will permit no prudential Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives (as they of <hi>Rome</hi> call them) to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:44247:42"/>
And yet even amongſt us, there are many ſharp and eager conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and diſputes, to which Scripture perhaps (if men were honeſt) would, but we ſee it doth not put an iſſue, and it may be never can for theſe two Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe all parties plead it, and pretend to it; yea that very Novel Sect among us, that at firſt ſo greatly diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged and contended againſt it. It is notoriouſly known what men had a hand in forming this Sect, and indeed there are many clear ſignatures upon the <hi>foetus,</hi> to enable us to judge who was the Parent, and amongſt the reſt this is one, and the deſign and policy in it plain, which was to diſparage the holy Scriptures, and bring them into diſeſteem and contempt (as they have always done) and then the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs was very eaſie, for the private Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit they could eaſily when they pleaſed take them off, by ſhewing it liable to a thouſand inconveniences, and when the Scripture was undervalued too, then the Catholick Church, and him
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:44247:43"/>
that they pretended to be the Infallible Head of it, was the next refuge.</p>
               <p>But theſe men ſoon ſaw that ſuch things would not long take in <hi>England,</hi> where all men generally have a great veneration for the Scriptures, and whom it is not eaſie to debauch into a total diſeſteem of them: and therefore now the ſcene is changed, and theſe men are permitted to pretend to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as ſtrongly as others, and all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable art uſed, that they may do it as plauſibly.</p>
               <p>And indeed it may too truly be ſaid, that this hath been the common refuge of almoſt all Hereticks, who by plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and perverting of it, have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to gain reputation to their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Hereſies.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For ſecondly, cunning men can make a ſhift to wreſt and pervert it: The truth is, the Originals in which it was written, are ſo very copious, that they are capable eaſily of various and different Interpretations. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a ſmall point, and a Comma makes a difference even to contrary
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:44247:43"/>
Expoſitions. It was ſo of old among the <hi>Jews,</hi> and it was ſo long ſince among Chriſtians (as S. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us) and we our ſelves ſadly ſee it to be ſo to this day.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now in theſe caſes I ask what men ſhall do? Two men equally pretend Scripture; and Two men give diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Expoſitions of the ſame Scripture; in this caſe what were a private Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian beſt to do? I know well enough what remedy the Learned might have: But it is ten to one a private Chriſtian cannot make uſe of the ſame, becauſe he doth not underſtand the Original Languages, much leſs the Criticiſms of them, and the cuſtoms of the places and people related to: Nor perhaps is ſo mighty well verſed in Scripture, as by comparing one place with another, to be able to collect the true ſenſe of all.</p>
               <p>In this caſe it is eaſie to ſee the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience of ſubſtituting this Rule only to judge by, becauſe it ſelf is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed, and equally pleaded by both,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:44247:44"/>
and every common Chriſtian cannot tell which of the Two it favoureth moſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Another thing pretended as a ſure Rule to judge by in this caſe, is a ſingle perſon; for whom we know what kind of men plead mightily, and contend highly that God hath veſted him with Infallibility, and deſigned him to be that lively Oracle to which the Church in all its doubts ought to reſort, and with whoſe determinations all men ſhould reſt ſatisfied, and be concluded: And I muſt needs ſay, were there any ſuch perſon, there were a ſhort and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie way of ſilencing all diſputes in the world.</p>
               <p>But againſt this I offer only theſe two conſiderations.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, That every man muſt be ſure of this Infallibility, or elſe he can never with any ſteddineſs remit all his doubts to his Infallibility. But we not only ſee that a great many of men plainly deny it, and almoſt all mightily doubt of it: But</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:44247:44"/>2. Secondly, are mightily ſatisfied, that no man ever can be ſure of it, not only becauſe God himſelf hath not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared a ſyllable of any ſuch thing, which he certainly would have done, had it been true, it being a thing of ſuch infinite moment, and ſo mightily concerning the world to know: But alſo becauſe it is evident, that ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have mightily erred, and nothing is more familiar than for one Pope to contradict the determinations, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal the Sanctions of another. And alſo becauſe they that moſt eagerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for this, do not know how to tell us, when we are to judge him Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible, and when not.</p>
               <p>And indeed the effects of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence have been ſo monſtrouſly pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as to prejudice ſufficiently all ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber men againſt it, who conſider that this very thing hath had a mighty hand in debauching Chriſtian Religion to thoſe horrid degrees, which we ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee at this day.</p>
               <p n="3">3. General Councils: And I confeſs I am one of thoſe who have a mighty
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:44247:45"/>
veneration for what juſt and lawful Councils ſhall determine, and I think it would be of great advantage to the peace of the Church, if all men had ſo too.</p>
               <p>But then I do not ſee why theſe ſhould be appealed to as the only Rule or Judges in theſe things: Not only becauſe they cannot be pretended to be Infallible, for they are men, and may erre, and they actually have done ſo: But alſo, ſhould we allow them a kind of Infallibility (for abſolute they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pretend to) yet it will not be eaſie for every ſingle perſon to know what they have determined; and upon every difference that aroſe, new Councils muſt be Convened, which is a thing next to impoſſible.</p>
               <p n="4">4. An immediate Spirit, which though ſome men ſo mainly contend for in this Age, and many have done formerly, there having been few or no Ages of the Church in which there have not been Enthuſiaſts, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to Divine Impulſes and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations: yet there are theſe two eternal exceptions againſt it.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:44247:45"/>1. That nothing more expoſeth men to the deluſions of that crafty Spirit of error than this doth: And it is moſt certain, that pretences to, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations of, and reliances on it, have been one of the chief cauſes of many ancient Hereſies, and of thoſe woful differences that are at preſent among us: And the wildeſt errors that have infeſted the Church have been fathered upon it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, That this alſo is to be tried by ſomething elſe, as S. <hi>John</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns, <hi>Verſe</hi> 1. of this Chapter, telling us, that many falſe Spirits are gone out into the world, and therefore making it neceſſary for all that would not be deluded by them, to make carefully a trial of them. And if the Spirit it ſelf be to be tried, it is not a Rule to try all things by.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Antiquity: And there is no doubt, but the ſtreams are always pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, that are neareſt to the fountain: and Chriſtianity flouriſhed in its puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and truth for ſome Centuries at the firſt. And if men would ſearch Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:44247:46"/>
and let the Primitive times de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine for them, there would not be ſo many conteſts as there are in the Chriſtian Church.</p>
               <p>But there is this unhappy and invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible exception againſt it, that it is mighty difficult, and next to impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, to know what Antiquity belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and practiſed in many caſes. We have but very little left us of the three firſt Centuries: And the greateſt Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and they that have travelled far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt in the ſearch of Antiquity, are at a mighty loſs, as to the knowledge of them: and therefore how every private Chriſtian ſhould be able upon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to have recourſe to it, and ſtill have it in readineſs to judge all things by, is very hard to determine.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Catholick Tradition; for which ſome men contend both eagerly and ſharply, and have racked ingenuity to ſay all that can be ſaid for it, and for what reaſons we know. And I do moſt readily acknowledge that a great deference ought to be had to it, and a greater than generally is: But ſtill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:44247:46"/>
all that can be ſaid, there are theſe two exceptions againſt it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That men cannot tell us what is a Catholick Tradition, and what is not ſo: at leaſt they can inſtance but in very few things that have unexcepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onably been owned for ſuch: ſince few things have ever been pretended ſuch, about which there have not been great diſputes and ſharp contentions.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Tradition is ſo very liable to corruption, and ſo very many plain inſtances can be given of its degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: Beſides all which, the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience ſtill preſſeth here too, for how all private Chriſtians ſhould be able to guide themſelves by this, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eaſily be ſhewed.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The authority of that Church of which a man is a preſent member. And there is no doubt, but every man ows a great reſpect to this, and ſhould not but in mighty plain and great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances ever think contrary to it: and there is as little doubt but it would be mighty advantagious, and of great uſe and benefit, for men to be ready to be
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:44247:47"/>
concluded by the determinations and Symbols and Canons of it, and I little queſtion but a private Chriſtian erring with this, ſhall have a great deal to plead for himſelf, and ſhall have great abatements made for his Error at the laſt day. But yet there are ſome excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt this being made an only Rule to judge by, and amongſt others theſe two.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That a man doth not know his own Church to be Infallible, for there is not any ſuch promiſe made to any particular Church upon Earth: And though a man may be mighty ready to be concluded by it, and in moſt doubts ſuffer that ſcale in which the Churches judgment lies to preponderate, and to over-rule all his leſſer ſcruples, yet till he be aſſured of its infallibility he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abſolutely commit his faith to the conduct of it, nor unqueſtionably per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it in every thing to determine for him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That then there might ſafely be as many different Creeds, as there are differing Churches upon the Earth:
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:44247:47"/>
and then there need not be ſo much diſputing about a true Church, nor hunting after marks of it; ſince the faith of every man's own Church would certainly ſave him, which I take to be a doctrine too bold for any man to believe, that exerciſeth his reaſon to any meaſures at all.</p>
               <p>I cannot eaſily remember any thing beſides theſe, that can be ſubſtituted as a Rule in this matter, but if I could, I do not at all doubt, but that it would appear liable to as many or more diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties than any of theſe: And I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but think theſe great inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that all and every one of theſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named are incumbred withal, are a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient reaſon upon which to reject them from being Rules in this caſe; eſpecially</p>
               <p n="4">4. If we compare this that I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending for, and conſider the evident advantages that it hath above them, and the leſs difficulties that it is preſſed withal. I have partly hinted before that there are theſe two things greatly needful in ſuch a Rule, facility, and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:44247:48"/>
ſafety; that it be both eaſie and ſafe to judge by: and I think it a fair offer, the Rule that bids faireſt in theſe two, let it be accepted. I ſhall therefore a while conſider it more abſolutely in it ſelf, in point both of eaſineſs and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and ſecondly, compare it a little with theſe that have been named, and intimate ſomething of the advantage and preference that it claims before them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is a Rule that is truly capable of both theſe characters: For firſt, it is eaſie to judge by; for few men but of common either knowledge or hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, can miſtake in judging what is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and what is not: ſeeing the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of theſe things is in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure imprinted on our very natures, and grows up with us.</p>
               <p>We need not go and conſult Oracles, nor ſay who ſhall aſcend into Heaven to fetch us a reſolution from thence;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.6, 7, 8.</note> for as <hi>Moſes</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> both ſay the Word is nigh us, even in our own hearts, there the great lines of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:44247:48"/>
duty are written legibly and plainly, and an honeſt (though meanly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed) mind will quickly attain the knowledge of them.</p>
               <p>So that a Heathen might, and ſome actually have judged pretty rightly in this inſtance: For as theſe give evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of a Law written in their hearts,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15.</note> as the Apoſtle tells us they do, ſo many of them that have attended cloſely to this connate light, have by it alone at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained almoſt to an exact knowledge in theſe things, and paſſed a right ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence upon all Opinions and Doctrines that did not conſent with the ſame.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſing a man in the profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſtianity, and under the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the written Law and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of God; we ſet him in infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly greater advantages; foraſmuch as all things of neceſſary duty are ſo clearly revealed and made known therein, that it is not very eaſie to be ignorant of, or not to underſtand them.</p>
               <p>And ſecondly, it is as ſafe to judge by it as it is eaſie to do ſo: For firſt, if
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:44247:49"/>
a judgment be truly made by it, it is infallibly certain; and any doctrine that truly tends to the promoting holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, is as undoubtedly Chriſtian and Divine, and true, as if God had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten it with his own hand: And every doctrine that truly promotes and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageth the practice of vice, is as certainly falſe and diabolical, as if we ſaw it proceed out of the mouth of the old Dragon. And ſecondly, if a man ſhould chance to erre, while he really and truly judgeth for this, I think it may ſafely be ſaid that error is not dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable: It is an error on the ſafer ſide, a miſtake on the better hand: A judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for God and his intereſt, where the will is honeſt and innocent and good, and where that is ſo, I do not know how to call any thing a ſin.</p>
               <p>This I take to be certain, an honeſt heart uſing its ſincere and true endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and intending really to embrace and follow that, which beſt teacheth its duty, and engageth to it, is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſafe. God's good Providence and Grace will ſuperintend and aſſiſt ſuch a
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:44247:49"/>
man, that he ſhall either not fall into any error at all, or at leaſt not into any damnable one: God's Spirit will lead him into all truth, that is really need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for him to know.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Should we now make a compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon between this and the others, upon theſe two things, we ſhould preſently ſee to which the advantage would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline. Some of them are not ſafe to judge by, and ſome not eaſie to do ſo, and ſome again neither of the two, as would eaſily be made appear, ſhould we again review, and diſtinctly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them; which becauſe I have not leiſure, or a mind to do my ſelf, I ſhall beg and truſt you or any other to do for me. I am ſure he will find all thoſe clogged with ſome inconveniences, from which this is either wholly, or in a great meaſure free; which I take to be a good reaſon, upon which to give it the preference above them.</p>
               <p>Not but that I can eaſily foreſee that this Rule alſo may be preſſed with ſome difficulties, and could we lay down a Rule which were not, we ſhould then
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:44247:50"/>
anticipate our future ſtate, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive a way to ſecure man from all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of error, which in this imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſtate is a thing rather to be wiſhed than hoped for: We muſt therefore in this make as good a ſhift as we can, and chuſe that as the ſafeſt, which leaſt ſubjects us unto error, or at leaſt to the feweſt: which becauſe this doth, I therefore propoſe it as the beſt thing to be attended to in this caſe: And only further add, that whatever miſtakes we may be ſubject to in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by this, we may in a great meaſure ſecure our ſelves from, by attending to thoſe directions for the management of this judgment, that the next Chapter will make known to us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:44247:50"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Six rules laid down to be obſerved by us in our judging by this rule, and three of theſe inſiſted upon.</head>
               <p>THE judging of all doctrines being ſomewhat a difficult thing, and no Rule to judge by being ſo mighty plain, but that men may be incident unto error in their applications of it (as the former Chapter intimated) it will be needful to contrive againſt that error as well as we can, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve from all miſapplying this Rule as much as may be: In order to which there are theſe ſix things which I ſhall preſcribe to be obſerved carefully by us in this matter.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That in our judging by this Rule, we conſider the doctrines only, and not the men that profeſs and maintain them.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:44247:51"/>2. That we conſider doctrines not only in themſelves, and ſpecious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, but in their natural and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect conſequences.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That we be ſincere and unpreju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced in conſidering, and do not allow our ſelves to pervert or wreſt them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That doctrines, or modes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be not conſidered only in ſome ſingle inſtances, but complexly and fully.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That men have a right notion of holineſs, and conſider duly both in what things it doth conſiſt, and all thoſe things too.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That holineſs be conſidered not only in its immediate exerciſe, but to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with all the helps, advantages and encouragements to it.</p>
               <p>Theſe are Rules enough to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by us in this matter, and I cannot eaſily foreſee any great inconveniences that we ſhall be preſſed with, or inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent unto, if we keep us cloſe, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend carefully to them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt is, that in our judging of things by this Rule, we conſider on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:44247:51"/>
the doctrines themſelves, and not the men that make profeſſion of them; for otherwiſe we ſhall be greatly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled, and perplexed in our thoughts, and in great danger of pronouncing wrong judgment, we may acquit the guilty, and condemn the innocent, we may be enſnared to embrace the worſt, and to caſt off the beſt and trueſt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines.</p>
               <p>There are few things more common, than to ſee Hereticks and venters of ſtrange and pernicious Doctrines, to behave themſelves with the greateſt ſeeming ſtrictneſs and caution of any men. Our Saviour therefore repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents them as wearing ſheeps cloathing,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.15.</note> the ſhew of a mighty innocence, and putting on the diſguiſe of all poſſible ſanctity: And S. <hi>Paul</hi> informs us of much-what the ſame thing, when he lays down among their other characters this of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a form of Godlineſs.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And the truth is, they were very imprudent and ſilly, if they ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:44247:52"/>
otherwiſe, this is the ſureſt way they can poſſibly take, to gain eſteem to themſelves, and reputation to the doctrines they would proſelyte men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a belief of: well knowing that error in its native dreſs and true colours would never be entertain'd by men, and therefore it is carefully apparell'd in a falſe and ſpecious garb, by which it ſteals mens affections, and cheats them into a love and eſteem of it. And as deſigning men cloath their doctrines, ſo commonly they do themſelves; for the firſt great buſineſs of a Seducer is to gain a reputation of being holy and good, which when it is once gotten, will eaſily inſinuate and make way for his doctrine; for men eaſily believe and follow ſuch men, and do not fear Impoſture from thoſe that they eſteem holy and good.</p>
               <p>And on the other hand, it is often (too often God knows) ſeen, that men detain the truth in unrighteouſneſs, believe well and Orthodoxly, and yet are falſe to their own faith, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous to their avowed principles, and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:44247:52"/>
never live conſonantly to either. And by this means greatly reproach and ſcandalize their own moſt holy profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the impure <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> did Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity at the firſt: And if the faith of ſuch men were to be meaſured by their lives, and the effects it hath on them, they were doubtleſs the greateſt Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks in all the world.</p>
               <p>This is a ſuggeſtion which as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flects a great deal of reproach and ſhame upon ſuch men, ſo it beſpeaks the great heed and care of others, that they be not haſty preſently to judge mens Religion only by their actions: For many men wear paints and diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to conceal a rotten faith; and too many are careleſs and fooliſh, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindful of adorning a true one.</p>
               <p>It were eaſie to cite the beſt Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to vouch the reaſonableneſs and prudence of practiſing this Rule. For therefore the primitive Fathers of the Church, when the ſeeming Sanctity of Heathens and Hereticks was objected to them, did ſtrongly endeavour to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their doctrines, and to ſhew that
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:44247:53"/>
ſuch things were not really the effects of them, but <hi>fucus</hi>'s and paints on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to give reputation to them. And when on the other hand, they were preſſed with the profane lives of ſome of their own way, they preſently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed to the principles of their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and throughly vindicated them, from any way influencing, or inclining men to ſuch evil things: And having done ſo, proceeded to diſclaim theſe men as falſe Brethren, and no true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, and therefore pleaded it an unjuſt thing to argue againſt Chriſtians from the impure lives of ſome that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, but begged it as a reaſonable thing, that they would allow them the ſame favour, which they themſelves challenged in the like caſe, <hi>viz.</hi> that the failings of ſome pretended Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans might no more be objected againſt the divinity and truth of that Religion, than the vices of ſome Philoſophers were thought meet, to diſparage the credit and truth of all Philoſophy.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond Rule is, that we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider doctrines not only in themſelves,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:44247:53"/>
and ſpecious appearances, but in thoſe conſequences that naturally and direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iſſue from them: For it is not more true of men, than of doctrines ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, that they put on a very ſpecious and fair outſide, and in their preſent appearance ſeem mighty innocent, which yet if a man cloſely inſpect, and ſearch into, he will ſoon find to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry poiſonous and deſtructive in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of them. This is always in ſome meaſure true of all Errors and Hereſies that are, one way or other they are pernicious in their intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and if they be purſued to their juſt conſequences, certainly deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive.</p>
               <p>Let me give you one <hi>ſpecimen</hi> of this inſtead of many, I would fain know what ſeems more innocent, and of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter effect, than that all men ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to that meaſure of light, that is in their own breaſts? Hearken carefully to that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (as ſome Ancients called a mans Conſcience) that good <hi>Genius</hi> in a man's own Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom: And doubtleſs it were good men
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:44247:54"/>
did this, and if they did ſo, they would act much better than many do.</p>
               <p>But yet who ſees not the danger that lurks under this fair pretence, and what horrid conſequences flow from it, when driven to its true purpoſe? How it wholly evacuates the ſatisfaction of Chriſt, and all neceſſity of a Saviour: Decries all need of Divine aſſiſtance and Grace: Renders wholly uſeleſs the Divine Inſpirations: Makes every man his own infallible Oracle and Teacher: Expoſeth a man to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of that ſubtil and watchful Spirit; and finally opens a way for every man to do that which is right in his own eyes.</p>
               <p>It were as eaſie to inſtance in ſome other doctrines of this mad Sect, and all others among us at this day, and ſhew how even the moſt innocent of them (I mean in which they differ from the Church) to be deadly and mighty miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous when purſued and driven home to their proper conſequences: and perhaps Sir, that may be done, if you require it, hereafter.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:44247:54"/>In the mean time, this will render it mighty neceſſary and wiſe, not to conſider erroneous doctrines only in their fair appearances, but to examine carefully what the conſequences and effects of them are.</p>
               <p>And ſo on the other ſide likewiſe, there are many doctrines in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion Orthodox and Divine, that perhaps at firſt ſight may appear very irrelative to practice, or at leaſt of no great moment to the purpoſes of life: Yea, which to ſome men may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear unreaſonable, and purely ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, which yet when a man hath exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined cloſely, and conſider well of, may be found very important, and greatly concerning, and very condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive to many real purpoſes of goodneſs. And it will not be eaſie to inſtance in any, which I cannot ſhew to be condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive to ſome great inſtances of holineſs, and whoſe truth and divinity I dare not undertake to make good by the ſame.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third Rule is, that we be ſincere and honeſt in our conſidering doctrines, before we bring them to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:44247:55"/>
this ſtandard. I mean that we bring with us no other deſign in the world, but really to know what ſuch doctrines are, and tend unto: For if any other thing be had in aim, any other deſign or prejudice be permitted to mingle with our ſearches into theſe things, there is no doubt but we ſhall deflect and warp from the truth in judgment. A very little skill if there be not a great deal of honeſty, will enable a man to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe any doctrine, and thoſe men that can ſo eaſily wreſt the holy Scriptures, doubtleſs can as eaſily pervert any do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine though never ſo holy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Facile eſt invenire baculum,</hi> ſaid the old adage, and it holds true both ways; he that comes either with a prejudice againſt, or a prepoſſeſſion for any doctrine, will eaſily find faults againſt the one, though never ſo ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, and ſomething to juſtifie his kindneſs to the other, though never ſo weakly aſſerted: And when men will permit intereſt or paſſion, or humour or prejudice, or any ſuch thing to ſit upon the Tribunal, and have a hand
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:44247:55"/>
in judging doctrines, it is not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected that they ſhould be judged ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the real merits and truth of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A gift,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, blindeth the eye,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.7.</note> 
                  <hi>or deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the heart,</hi> and a recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of them is ſeldom upright. And it is equally true of any other by-reſpect or ſiniſter inclination. Nothing but a fixed reſolution and purpoſe to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and juſt, and truly to inform our ſelves, can enable us to be true to our diſcoveries, and pronounce aright con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning doctrines in this caſe.</p>
               <p>It was no very unreaſonable project in the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> of old, to inſtitute ſome previous purgations of mind, to be ſubmitted unto by thoſe that were in queſt of truth, well knowing that till the mind of man was unprejudiced and free, it was not capable of Divine irradiations, nor in a capacity to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand truth. And upon the ſame reaſon <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> prohibited young men the ſtudy of Moral Philoſophy, till they had in ſome competent meaſure ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:44247:56"/>
the vigour, and tamed the hurry of their animal paſſions, and ſenſual in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations. And it were very well if men would do ſomething like this, free themſelves from all manner of partial anticipations, when they are going to conſider and judge for their Souls.</p>
               <p>And let me add Sir, there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any age wherein the obſervation of this Rule was more neceſſary, never a time certainly wherein the effects of partiality and prejudice more diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelves, to the warping of mens judgments, and clapping falſe biaſſes upon them, ſo that they either cannot, or will not impartially and truly weigh things, or deal with any degree of candor by them: wherein unjuſtly to pervert and miſrepreſent Books, is to anſwer them, and the faſtening on them a deſign which the Author never thought of, a ſufficient confutation of them: When men read Books on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to miſunderſtand and traduce them, and think the moſt effectual way to baffle and defeat them, is to buffoon and turn them into <hi>Ridicule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:44247:56"/>Let me give you a few <hi>ſpecimens</hi> of this, though I doubt not you have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready obſerved them your ſelf.</p>
               <p>Can you think we ſhould ever have heard of a <hi>Rehearſal Tranſproſed,</hi> or an Ill Play thought a good anſwer to a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Book, had not this perverſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour poſſeſſed ſome men that were proud of their great wits, and too fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful to be able truly to conſider things?</p>
               <p>Could any honeſt-hearted man, that ſincerely read over an excellent Book, called <hi>The Deſign of Chriſtianity,</hi> ever have traduced it as a plain undermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the purpoſe of the Goſpel?</p>
               <p>Had we ever heard of an <hi>Antiſozzo,</hi> or a <hi>Melius Inquirendum,</hi> if that Author had had as much honeſty as he thinks he hath wit? or conſidered the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines in thoſe Books (he would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) with half as much integrity, as he hath taken pains unworthily to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſent them?</p>
               <p>Can you imagine Satan would ever have been brought upon the ſtage com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plementing <hi>Sherlock,</hi> if the Devil had not mightily aſſiſted one <hi>Danſon,</hi> to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:44247:57"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:44247:57"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:44247:58"/>
miſunderſtand and pervert the deſign of that Book?</p>
               <p>Could that perfidious doating Exil'd <hi>Frenchman</hi> have ever eſpied and repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſuch advances of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to Popery, had not himſelf made greater advances firſt towards Frenzy or Knavery?</p>
               <p>Or the late furious Collector of the <hi>Invidious Parallels</hi> made ſuch a clamor with them, and ſeek ſo baſely to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb the Aſhes, and deface the Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of thoſe that reſt in honour, but that ſomething made a noiſe in his own head, and hindred him from hearing or attending to the checks of his own Conſcience for ſuch a piece of inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice?</p>
               <p>I pray God Sir, deliver you and me, and bleſs us from falling into the hands of ſuch men, who read Books on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to miſunderſtand them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider doctrines only to expoſe them: who react the cruelty and injuſtice of Ancient Perſecutors, that cloathed the poor Chriſtians in skins of Beaſts, and then glutted their malice and envy in
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:44247:58"/>
worrying of them: And deal with Books as <hi>Procruſtes</hi> did with men, rack them till they come up to their own humour, or cut them in pieces for not doing ſo: Who firſt tincture their own eye, and then apprehend every thing to be of the ſame colour; or having their own palates vitiated, reproach as unſavoury and bitter every thing that comports not with the ill affections of it.</p>
               <p>If it be my hard fate to fall into the hands of ſuch men, and be treated by them as ſome of my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren have been, I will yet have this to comfort and ſupport me, that it is not truth or honeſty, but ſpleen and malice only that perſecute me. I ſhould be concerned indeed, ſhould I offend the firſt; but if men acted by the other ſpeak evil of me, I know who hath bade me rejoyce and be glad.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="chapter">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:44247:59"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> The Fourth, Fifth and Sixth Rules are mentioned and inſiſted on.</head>
               <p n="4">4. THE fourth Rule is, that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Modes of Religion formed by them, be not conſidered on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſome ſingle inſtances, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexly and fully in all together. I mean, that we take not only ſome few particular doctrines of a Sect or Mode of Religion, and ſingly conſider them, and paſs a judgment upon all only by them: But that we take a view of all its parts, and examine every inſtance of it throughly, eſpecially all thoſe in which it differs from others.</p>
               <p>For as there is very rarely or never any Error without ſome mixture of Truth, the more to ſet it off, and give
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:44247:59"/>
it credit: No more is there any Sect, any way of Religion who doth not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and teach ſome excellent Truth, and own ſome very wholſom doctrines: And it will therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern every man that would not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trapped by them, not only to conſider ſome few, but the whole maſs of their doctrines and belief.</p>
               <p>Some things we may light of in the Symbols of all parties that may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, and true, and good, but others, in many, that are as really diabolical and untrue: And he that will be indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by thoſe good things, to paſs a judgment upon all, is imprudent and unwiſe, and may eaſily be induced to abſolve the moſt pernicious doctrines that were ever vented by any Heretick in the world. The old Maxim is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to be conſidered here, and it holds true in this inſtance as ſtrongly as in any others, to render a thing truly good there muſt be a concurrence of all cauſes, when a failure in one is enough to render a thing evil.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:44247:60"/>And therefore though a Sect do ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly maintain, and earneſtly contend for twenty great Truths, yet if it take into its Symbols of belief, one groſs Error, that plainly contradicts the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of Religion, and eſtabliſheth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience and vice in any one inſtance, it is a ſufficient warrant for us to reject it upon: and we ought not in that caſe to plead the many truths it maintains, for in them it Symbolizeth with the Church, and holds them in common with it: But upon the other it ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and makes the Schiſm, and takes its denomination from, and therefore by thoſe eſpecially is to be acquitted or condemned.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Th fifth Rule is, that we be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſtill that we have a right notion of holineſs, according to which we are to judge, for if we miſtake here, and do not underſtand rightly our own Rule, we ſhall certainly erre in our judging by it. There are two things that I intend in this ſuggeſtion. 1. That we do truly underſtand in what things
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:44247:60"/>
holineſs and real goodneſs doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt. 2. That we conſider all thoſe things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That we do really underſtand in what things holineſs and the practice of goodneſs doth conſiſt: For I obſerve that many are very apt to miſtake here, and to place holineſs in the practice of things, which ſignifie little or nothing to the real purpoſes of it.</p>
               <p>It hath been an Error as ancient as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> time, to Tithe Mint, and Anniſe, and Cummin, and yet neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the weightier things of the Law, as Juſtice, Mercy, and Faithfulneſs: And the Error hath been tranſcribed in all Ages ſince: For ſo ſome men have been mighty exact in the Ceremonial parts of Religion, and yet greatly neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lective of the real: And others have choſen to themſelves ſome little eaſie things, and laid great weight upon them, while the more ſubſtantial and arduous duties have been diſregarded by them: Subſtituted ſome cheap tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling performances, in the place of real
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:44247:61"/>
obedience to Gods commands: Placed Religion in a habit, or a dreſs, or a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure look, or a diſtinct form of ſpeech, or ſome little <hi>Shiboleth</hi> or other, and by exactneſs in theſe preſently conclude themſelves reformed, and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the pollutions of other men.</p>
               <p>I do not go to enquire into the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of men's doing thus, they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready too plain, men can in theſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie their Luſts, and their Conſciences too, indulge their pride, and intereſt, and eaſe, and yet in ſome meaſure pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie their own minds, for they do not wholly neglect Religion, only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mute the great duties of it into ſome cheaper performances, by which as they make a ſhift to gull their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, ſo they may get a reputation among men, before whom theſe things make a great and glaring ſhow, and a mighty noiſe, when faithfulneſs, and mercy, and truth, and humility, and the other great inſtances of real good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are more ſecret and unobſerved,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:44247:61"/>
and boaſt not themſelves ſo before men.</p>
               <p>This therefore is a Rule that's migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty neceſſary to be attended unto, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in this Age, in which <hi>Phariſaiſm</hi> is ſo much revived, and men's Religion dwindled into appearances, and outſide, and fair ſhews, and mere pageantry. So that if we judge preſently here by outward appearance, we ſhall go near to judge unrighteous judgment: But if we conſider that holineſs doth not conſiſt in theſe things, we ſhall go near to preſerve our ſelves from any over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuing of them.</p>
               <p>For in ſuch a caſe the truth rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines the other way, and whenever we ſee men mighty exact and critical in theſe little things, and eager conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for them, and placing great holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in them, and diſtinguiſhed from their Brethren only by them: It is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a ſure ſign, that ſuch men are either fools or knaves: Fools in being cheated by the great enemy to take up in little things, and ſcramble about
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:44247:62"/>
them, and in the mean time be diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from thoſe great things upon which Holineſs and Salvation do depend: Or knaves in being exact in theſe, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to conceal their failure in the other. Theſe times let us ſee, that this is too commonly the real caſe, you ſhall rarely or never ſee, but there is ſome latent imperfection, where the paint and the outward dreſs is ſo extremely curious; for men never uſe ſo much art, as when they are purpoſing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive. Sincerity contents it ſelf with a very plain garb, while no curioſity and care is thought too much for the Hypocrite.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, That we conſider all theſe things too: For if we judge by ſome only, we may erre mightily here too. There are few men ſo bad, as not to be careful in ſome things, and to hope by thoſe to expiate their diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of others: And none but thoſe that have never converſed with men, can but know how uſual it is to have men hope, that one inſtance of vertue
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:44247:62"/>
ſhall compenſate for the want of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that one good deed ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe another ſin. For ſo he that is a drunkard, can plead that he is juſt, and he that is unjuſt can alledge his fearing of an oath, and while either of theſe can do the one, they hope God will pardon them for being the other: This I take to be one great reaſon why ſo many halt in duty, and content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with a partial and imperfect obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
               <p>And as it is with ſingle men, ſo it is commonly with aggregate Sects: There are few of theſe which are not mighty zealous for ſome good things, and by this hope either to conceal from men, or obtain pardon from God, for their remiſneſs in others. So that we muſt be careful not to paſs a judgment only by ſome few things, but to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whether this pompous zeal and care extend it ſelf equally to all both ſins and duties, for if it do not, it is far from being that zeal that is according to Godlineſs; for that is a regular
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:44247:63"/>
thing, and hath an equal regard to every thing that is a duty, and an equal abhorrence of every thing that is a ſin.</p>
               <p>This is a thing of great advantage to be conſidered by us, and by it we may go near to diſcover almoſt all diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of men that are. It is a thing well worth the notice of men, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how the Catalogue of ſins is leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſened, and ſtruck up into a very little room by moſt of the Sects among us at this day: who though they be great declaimers againſt the ſins of the times, yet they mean commonly no more but ſwearing, and drunkenneſs, and whoredom, and murther by thoſe ſins: while covetouſneſs and pride, faction and Schiſm, uncharitableneſs and cenſoriouſneſs, and falſe accuſing their Brethren; diſobedience to ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, and blaſpheming dignities, and ſuch like, are connived at, not cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as ſins, or perhaps commended as innocent things. I do moſt heartily acknowledge the former are very hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:44247:63"/>
vices, and can never too much be declaimed againſt in an age ſo inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to them: But I know as well that the others too are ſins as damning as they; and it argues but an ill ſpirit, and ſmells very rankly of hypocriſie, to cry out ſo much againſt the one, and yet hug and cheriſh and indulge the other.</p>
               <p>And it fares no better with the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of duties, which is leſſen'd by ſome men proportionably to the other, and the commandments reduced too at pleaſure that do preſcribe them. It hath been objected to the ſhame of Papiſts, that they have quite expung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Second Precept of the Firſt Table out of the Decalogue, and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Tenth to make up the number: And I think all honeſt men have juſt cauſe to condemn them for it: But upon the ſame reaſon that they are condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, are thoſe too that expunge all the Six of the Second Table as ſome do, and the Fifth, Ninth and Tenth as almoſt all do, eſpecially of thoſe that infeſt us.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:44247:64"/>
It hath been long ſince obſerved how the Claſſis and the Conclave have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly agreed in the violation of the Fifth Commandment; And in their doctrines about Government, and obedience to it: But I think it no great adventure to tell you, that not only theſe men, but every other Faction of what denomination ſoever amongſt us do the ſame too. And if the old ſaying be true, that <hi>ex ungue leonem,</hi> then we may perhaps conjecture who hath had a hand in all theſe doctrines, and who doth indeed moſtly ſymbolize with Papiſts, They or the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that they ſo much cry out againſt in this matter.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Sixth and Laſt Rule is, that we conſider holineſs not only in its im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate act and exerciſe, but take in alſo the helps and advantages and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements to it: For there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny differences about doctrines that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly reſpect theſe: And though they do not immediately concern the exerciſe of holineſs, yet foraſmuch
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:44247:64"/>
as they relate to thoſe things which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to that, exerciſe, and are great helps to it, therefore they are diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nible by this Rule.</p>
               <p>Thus (for inſtance) a doctrine that more lively repreſents the advantages of holineſs and a good life: that more ſolidly evinceth the neceſſity of it: that adds more excellent and endearing encouragements to purſue it: that more fully aſſures a man of Divine aid and aſſiſtance in his endeavours after it; I ſay doctrines that beſt do all or any of theſe things, have a good ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon them, and bring with them a very great argument of their Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Truth: And this is a very good reaſon upon which to prefer them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore others, that either wholly fail to do theſe things, or at leaſt come far ſhort of the other for the ſolidneſs and clearneſs of doing ſo.</p>
               <p>The truth is Sir, a very great many of doctrines about which men diſpute and differ ſo eagerly at this day, may be decided clearly and ſafely by this
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:44247:65"/>
Rule: particularly all the controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies ſtated by the Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> and thoſe that depend on them: It will be no hard matter for a man of a common capacity to diſcover clearly, which ſide of theſe queſtions gives the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rableſt account of God Almighty, both as to his Attributes and dealings with the ſons of men: which moſt magnifie his love, and grace, and goodneſs to his Creatures: which moſt clearly aſſert and reconcile his wiſdom, and holineſs, and juſtice, and goodneſs: which moſt honourably explain and ſtate the Divine Philanthropy in the great acts of redemption performed by the Son of God: which moſt intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently and conſiſtently explain the three great offices of the holy <hi>Jeſus:</hi> and fortifie the hopes of the ſons of men in endeavouring after Salvation by all theſe.</p>
               <p>Again, which of the two doth moſt ſolidly evince the neceſſity of holineſs and a good life, and lay the more firm and aſſured foundation upon which
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:44247:65"/>
to ſuperſtruct that neceſſity: Which doth add the moſt preſſing Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Motives, and moſt ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally excite the endeavours of men af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it: And laſtly, which doth more lively encourage and animate thoſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, with aſſurance of Divine aſſiſtance and aid, to help the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and ſupply the imperfections of them.</p>
               <p>And by this may all the <hi>Antinomian</hi> Errors (which I take to be but the Tenets of the old <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> newly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived) and all ſuch wild opinions about Faith and Juſtification by it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be clearly diſcerned and judged too: And to conclude, whatever do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine fails in ſtating any of theſe things, which are ſo very neceſſary to encourage and help men in the way of goodneſs, may ſafely be rejected as an iſſue from the Spirit of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</p>
               <p>I content my ſelf Sir, only to give ſhort touches on all theſe Rules, and to ſay only ſo much as may make the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:44247:66"/>
reaſonableneſs of attending to them to appear: After which, every thing that might be added would appear te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, and I think it not good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to be burthenſom to any.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:44247:66"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Some Inferences made from this Collection, particularly a Vindication of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which may challenge any Sect at this day to joyn iſſue upon this Principle.</head>
               <p>HAving now given all needful aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to this Truth, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the right and ſafe manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it: I ſhall proceed to make an inference or two from it, before I put a period to this Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That it is very poſſible by attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this Rule, to put a ſpeedy end and iſſue to all diſputes that are in the Chriſtian world: And I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:44247:67"/>
there are no Rules we can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed by, ſo probable to do this with effect, as this is: Nor any thing by which private Chriſtians might ſo ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfully ſecure themſelves from all mortal Errors as by attending to this. And if the diſputing men of the Age proceeded by this meaſure, and ſtudied as much to expoſe the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, as to diſplay the falſhood of Opinions, their labour would be leſs, and their ſucceſs more: Men may ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er diſcern good from evil, than true from falſe: A little meaſure of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and honeſty, will enable men to do the firſt, but it requires a quick judgment ſometimes to do the ſecond; for falſhood wears the mantle of truth, and many times it is no eaſie thing to diſcover the Impoſtor: And ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing men honeſt, they are more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally convinced by the wickedneſs of an Opinion, than by any arguments of its untruth: For they do not know but men may impoſe upon them in theſe, but they can judge themſelves in the other.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:44247:67"/>And I ſhould think theſe two things were enough to recommend this way of determining controverſies to the Scribes and the Diſputers of this world: Since it would reduce the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies to a narrow compaſs, and men would more effectually be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by a ſolid determination upon that iſſue: and conſequently by this means they would ſooner be end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For firſt, there are few people ſo impudent, and paſt ſhame, as to plead openly for <hi>Baal;</hi> and contend for doctrines that every one ſees to be introductive of wickedneſs: Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors generally take another courſe, and gild their Pills, and wrap their poiſons in ſweet and gay appearances; and let the Opinions they would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote be never ſo pernicious, yet they are always managed with mighty pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of zeal and piety; and by this they hope to prevail more, than by all their ſubtil Arguments and fine
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:44247:68"/>
Diſputings; and indeed they do ſo, and ſimple honeſt people are eaſily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trapped by them, who have not time or skill, or both, to ſearch into the bottom of all their doctrines: So that to encounter with them upon this, were to rob them of that in which their ſtrength moſtly lieth, it were to ſuit the Antidote to the Poiſon, and to diſarm Hereſie of that weapon by which it doth the moſt miſchief; it were to uncaſe the Wolf, and ſhew what really he is, which would more affect men with horror and hatred of him, than ten thouſand fine diſcourſes about him would be able to do.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For ſecondly, bleſſed be God, men (eſpecially that pretend Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) are not ſo far debauched, but that they retain a veneration for piety and goodneſs, and a ſecret abhorrence of ſin and profaneneſs: Many that live in the one, yet condemn themſelves in it, and moſt men though far from being good themſelves, yet have a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:44247:68"/>
eſteem and love for thoſe that are: And therefore when Errors are truly diſcovered, and the impiety of them made known, then the Net is ſpread in the ſight of the Bird, and men are arm'd againſt the fine pleas, and the enchanting pretences for them, and are hardly proſelyted into a belief of them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And thirdly, when the diſputes are brought to this iſſue, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt is upon it, and nothing left to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, but which doctrine tends to make men holy, and which doth not ſo; then the judgment and the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination is more eaſily made: For (as I hinted before) the lines of duty are plain, and not ſo ſubject to thoſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties of miſtakes that other things are: Almoſt all practical things are plain, and eaſily underſtood, unleſs it be in ſome rare caſes: And for the moſt part diſputes and queſtions about them, do more perplex and intangle, than they do unfold and explain them:
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:44247:69"/>
About theſe every honeſt man is in a good meaſure able to inſtruct himſelf, ſuppoſing him to have any competent knowledge, and better able to judge, than he is of queſtions that are curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly managed, with great skill and art on both ſides.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And fourthly, for Controverſies and Diſputes that no way concerned holineſs, or related to it, men would ſoon perceive them to be impertinent and needleſs, and the purſuing of them to miniſter only to Faction and Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and ſo would concern themſelves neither one way or other about them; but let them fall to the ground, with as little notice taken of them, as there was reaſon to ſtart them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But the great deſign of theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and therefore the chief Inference I intend from this Subject, is for the Vindication of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and of the Reformed Religion profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by it. To this Rule it may moſt
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:44247:69"/>
ſafely appeal, and not fear to be tried by it: And as Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> ſaith, <hi>The God that anſwereth by Fire let him be God.</hi> If amongſt all competitions and contending Sects among us, there be any to be found that doth exceed, or equal her for conformity to this Rule, they ſhall readily have the right hand of fellowſhip, and due precedence yielded to them: And I challenge any of them all to joyn iſſue with her upon this principle. And certainly this is a very fair offer, ſince all the Separations amongſt us have been commenced up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this pretence: They have firſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from her, and then from each other, upon pretences of impurity in her Communion, and in queſt of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter purity ſtill.</p>
               <p>If a man therefore offer to make good theſe two things:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That there is no reaſon at all for Separation upon this account; nor juſt cauſe to object unholineſs and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity againſt her: Let her Articles
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:44247:70"/>
and Homilies be examin'd, her Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy as cloſely conſidered as may be: and if there be any thing in either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to holineſs, then condemn her and ſpare not, ſhe will (I am ſure) acknowledge her error, and patiently endure a reproof for it. But I defie any man living to do this, provided he exerciſe but any meaſure of charity and honeſty in expounding things: and do not imitate the ſeverity of that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <hi>Momus,</hi> who rather than find no fault in the Picture of <hi>Venus,</hi> would quarrel with her ſlip-ſhooe, and whoſe Motto in hunting for faults is, <hi>Aut in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniam aut faciam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That all and every of thoſe ways, and forms of Religion that theſe men have deflected unto, are much inferior to her in this matter: and may clearly be detected to be falſe by this Rule, ſince every one of them eſpouſeth do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines which either immediately, or in their juſt conſequences are intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductive of wickedneſs, and contrary
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:44247:70"/>
to holineſs in ſome inſtance or other.</p>
               <p>He, I ſay, that offers to make good both theſe things, as he will do a good ſervice to the Church, ſo he will do that which may juſtly ſhame and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the ſeveral contending Factions that have ſo unjuſtly and unreaſonably ſeparated from her: Now theſe are truths which no man need fear under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking to make good, and perhaps a <hi>ſpecimen</hi> of them may ere long ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
               <p>In the mean time I think it mine own, and intimate it as the duty of others too, to bleſs God, and give him our heartieſt praiſe, that hath cauſed us to be brought up in ſuch a Church whoſe Faith is truly Chriſtian and Primitive, and that Faith which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Godlineſs, whoſe Worſhip is truly Pious, and Grave, and Seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as ſuch ſhould be: All whoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Articles, whoſe Offices
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:44247:71"/>
and Ceremonies are truly adapted to promote the ſame amongſt all her Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries: And if Salvation be to be had in Communion with any Church in the World, I am ſure it is in ſuch an One.</p>
               <p>And to this to add a ſerious reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to adhere ſtedfaſtly to the ſame, and not permit our ſelves, like fools and children to be turned to and fro with every ſlight of doctrine, by cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and deſigning men: whoſe Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt or whoſe Paſſion, and ſome pitiful low deſign oblige them to defame and deſtroy her, and to make Factions and Rents in her, as the moſt certain me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods unto both.</p>
               <p>And (to conclude this Inference) when we are importuned and ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by any of theſe, and take upon us to judge of the Doctrines offer'd to us, let us not ſo much conſider the fine pleas that ſubtil men make for them, but bring them to this touchſtone, and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:44247:71"/>
try them honeſtly and carefully by it, and we ſhall ſoon ſatisfie our ſelves, and find enough to preſerve us againſt the infection of them, and as S. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>Hereby know the Spirit of Truth and the Spirit of Error.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="128" facs="tcp:44247:72"/>
            <head>The Concluſion.</head>
            <p>AND now Sir, I have finiſhed that trouble which I intend to give you at this time. I am very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that beſides the imperfections at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending what I have done, there are two or three things greatly wanting to complete this deſign, and worthy of a larger conſideration, being but only lightly touched in theſe Papers.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To Vindicate all the Articles in the Chriſtian Faith by this Rule, and ſhew the conduciveneſs of each to the great purpoſe of Holineſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, To joyn iſſue with all Hereſies, and the conſiderable Sects and Opinions that diſturb the peace of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:44247:72"/>
the Church at preſent, upon this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion: and try if the Principles of them all be not condemnable by this Rule.</p>
            <p>But Sir, theſe are things which will take up more time than at preſent I can ſpare to them: And I am willing to ſee how you reſent this that I have done, before I burthen you with more. But to let you ſee how wholly I am at your command, provided you remit me to my own time (us I am ſure you will) I promiſe to do in theſe what you think fit to require of me: Being extremely deſirous in every thing ſo to acquit my ſelf, as may ſecure me the reputation and honour of being</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
